<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition of the doctrine of the Catholic Church in matters of controversie by the Right Reverend James Benigne Bossuet ... ; done into English from the fifth edition in French.</title>
            <title>Exposition de la doctrine de l'Eglise catholique sur les matières de controverse. English</title>
            <author>Bossuet, Jacques Bénigne, 1627-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77108</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223808</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875650</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875650</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49682</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77108)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 810:7 or 2285:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition of the doctrine of the Catholic Church in matters of controversie by the Right Reverend James Benigne Bossuet ... ; done into English from the fifth edition in French.</title>
                  <title>Exposition de la doctrine de l'Eglise catholique sur les matières de controverse. English</title>
                  <author>Bossuet, Jacques Bénigne, 1627-1704.</author>
                  <author>Johnston, Joseph, d. 1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22, 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Exposition de la doctrine de l'Église catholique sur les matières de controverse.</note>
                  <note>Translated by Henry Joseph Johnston, O.S.B. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.) II, p. 242.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴,²B-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Page 16 of first numbered sequence misnumbered 19.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: Newberry Library and the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49682:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49682:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXPOSITION OF THE DOCTRINE OF THE Catholic Church IN MATTERS OF Controverſie.</p>
            <p>By the Right Reverend <hi>JAMES BENIGNE BOSSUET,</hi> Counſellor to the King, Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> formerly of <hi>Condom,</hi> and Preceptor to the Dauphin; Firſt Almoner to the Dauphineſs.</p>
            <p>Done into <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the Fifth Edition in <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:49682:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49682:2"/>
            <head>The <hi>Approbation</hi> of the Right Reverend, the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE have read the Treatiſe intituled, <hi>An Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Doctrine of the Catholic Church in Matters of Controverſie, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Right Reverend</hi> James Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignus Boſſuet, <hi>Biſhop and Lord of</hi> Condom, <hi>Preceptor to his Royal Highneſs, the Dauphin.</hi> And we declare, That after having examined it, with as much application as the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the matter required, we have found the Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it to be conformable to the Catholic Apoſtolic and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Faith. And therefore we think our ſelves obliged to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, as ſuch, to thoſe whom God has committed to our charge. We are certain, the Faithful will be edified by it, and we hope thoſe of the Pretended Reform'd Religion, who will read this Work with attention, will receive from it ſo right an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding as may conduce to put them into the way of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHARLES MAURICE LE TELLIER,</hi> Archbiſhop and Duke of <hi>Reims.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CH. de ROSMADEC,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tours.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>FELIX,</hi> Biſhop and Earl of <hi>Chalons.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>De GRIGNAN,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Uſez.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>D. DE LIGNY,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Meaux.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>NICHOLAS,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Auxerre.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>GABRIEL,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Autun.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>MARC,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tarbe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ARMAND JOHN,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Beziers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>STEPHEN,</hi> Biſhop and Prince of <hi>Grenoble.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>JULIUS,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tule.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:49682:3"/>
            <head>A Table of Articles contained in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> DEſign of this Treatiſe. <hi>Pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Thoſe of the Pretended Reform'd Religion acknowledg, That the Catholic Church embraces all the Fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian Religion. <hi>Pag. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Religious Worſhip is terminated only in God. <hi>Pag. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Invocation of Saints. <hi>Pag. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Images and Reliques. <hi>Pag. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Juſtification. <hi>Pag. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Merits of Good Works. <hi>Pag. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Satisfactions, Purgatory, and Indulgences. <hi>Pag. 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Sacraments. <hi>Pag. 19</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Baptiſm. <hi>Pag. 20</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Confirmation. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Pennance and Sacramental Confeſſion. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Exream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction. <hi>Pag. 21</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Marriage. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Holy Orders. <hi>Pag. 22</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Doctrine of the Church touching the real Preſence of the Body and Blood of <hi>JESUS CHRIST</hi> in the Euchariſt, and how the Church underſtands theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body. Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> Explication of theſe Words, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me. Pag. 25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> Explication of the Doctrine of the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> concerning the real Preſence. <hi>Pag. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> Of Tranſubſtantiation, and Adoration, and in what ſenſe the Euchariſt is a Sign. <hi>Pag. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> Sacrifice of the Maſs. <hi>Pag. 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews. Pag. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> Reflections upon the precedent Doctrine. <hi>Pag. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> Communion under both Species. <hi>Pag. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> The Written, and unwritten Word. <hi>Pag. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> The Authority of the Church. <hi>Pag. 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XX.</hi> The Opinions of the Pretended Reform'd upon the Authority of of the Church. <hi>Pag. 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXI.</hi> Authority of the Holy See, and of Epiſcopacy. <hi>Pag. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> Concluſion of this Treatiſe. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49682:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An</hi> Advertiſement <hi>upon</hi> Account <hi>of this</hi> Preſent Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
            <p>ONE would have thought thoſe of the pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, in reading this Treatiſe, ſhould at leaſt have granted that the Doctrine of the Church was faithfully Expounded in it. The leaſt they could have allowed a Biſhop, was to have underſtood his own Religion, and to have ſpoke without diſguiſe, in a matter, where to diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble would be a crime. But nevertheleſs it has fallen out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. This Treatiſe, whilſt a Manuſcript, was made uſe of to inſtruct ſeveral particular perſons, and many Copies of it were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed. Upon which the ſincerer part of the pretendedly Reform'd were almoſt every where heard to ſay, That if it were approved, it would in reality take away great difficulties; But that the Author durſt never publiſh it, and if he ſhould, he would not eſcape the cenſure of all thoſe of his Communion, not particularly of <hi>Rome,</hi> which would not frame it ſelf to his Maxims. After ſome time nevertheleſs, this Book, thus condemned to a perpetual obſcurity, appeared uſhered in with the Approbation of ſeveral Biſhops; And the Author, who knew very well he had only expreſſed in it the mind of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> apprehended not thoſe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures threatned by the Reformers.</p>
            <p>It was not certainly probable that the Catholick Faith ſhould be betrayed, inſtead of being expounded, by a Biſhop; who, after having preached the Goſpel all his life time, without the leaſt ſuſpicion of his Doctrine, had been newly called to inſtruct a Prince, whom the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt King in the World, and the moſt zealous Defender of the Religion of his Anceſtors, cauſes to be Educated in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that he may be one day one of its principal ſupports. But theſe Gentlemen of the pretended Reformation ceaſed not to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in their firſt Opinion. They expected every moment when Catholicks ſhould oppoſe this Book, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf condemn it.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this their imagination was, that the major part, who know nothing of our Doctrine, but as repreſented to them by their Miniſters under the moſt hideous Ideas, know it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain when ſhewn in its natural dreſs. So that it was no hard task to repreſent to them the Author of the Expoſition, as one who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49682:4"/>mollified the Sentiments of his Religion; and ſought out proper and qualifying moderations to content all Parties.</p>
            <p>There has appeared two Anſwers to this Treatiſe. The Author of the firſt would not diſcover his name,<note place="margin">M. Claude, de Langle, Daille, &amp; Alix.</note> and till he himſelf be pleaſed to declare it, we will not reveal the ſecret. It is enough to us that this work was approved by the Miniſters of <hi>Charenton,</hi> and ſent to the Author of the Expoſition by the late <hi>M. Conrart,</hi> one endowed with all that Catholicks could deſire in a Man,<note place="margin">An. p. 3. 112, 113, 124.137, &amp;c.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting a better Religion. The other Anſwer was written by <hi>M. Noguier</hi> a Miniſter, who is amongſt them of great repute, and has the eſteem of an able Divine.<note place="margin">Nog. p. 63, 94, 95, 109, 110. An. p. 10. Nog. p. 40. Nog. p. 20, 27.</note> They both pretended the Expoſition was contrary to the deciſions of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> They both affirm the very deſign it ſelf of expounding the Doctrine of the Council, to be prohibited by the <hi>Pope:</hi> And they both take care to ſay, that <hi>M. de Condom</hi> does only mince and extenuate the Doctrine of his Religion. As they repreſent him, one would think that he relents,<note place="margin">An. Avert. p. 24.</note> that he is coming over to them, that he abandons the Sentiments of his own Church,<note place="margin">Rep. p. 3. An. p. 137. Nog. p. 94. An Avert. p. 25, 26, 27, 28, 29.</note> and embraces thoſe of the Pretended Reform'd. In fine, his Treatiſe agrees not with that Profeſſion of Faith, which the Roman Church propoſes to all thoſe who are of her Communion, and they repreſent him at defiance with every Article.</p>
            <p>If we believe the <hi>Anonymus,</hi> this Prelate is come to a fair com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition about Tranſubſtantiation. He is willing to content himſelf with ſuch a reality of the Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the Sacrament as the Pretended Reform'd themſelves believe.<note place="margin">An. Avert. p. 27.</note> When he treats of the Invocation of Saints, <hi>He endeavours to mitigate and extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate this worſhip of the Roman Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An. p. 24.</note> both as to her Tenets and Practice. Together with the Veneration of Saints, <hi>he ſoftens that of Images,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An. p. 24. An. p. 65.</note> 
               <hi>as alſo the Articles of Satisfaction, Sacrifice of the Maſs, and the Popes Authority.</hi> As for Images, <hi>he is aſhamed of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to which the Doctrine as well as Practice has been carried.</hi> The <hi>Anonymus,</hi> who repreſents him as if he had changed the Council of <hi>Trents</hi> expreſſion in the Article of Satisfaction,<note place="margin">p. 110.</note> will needs have it, that <hi>this change in the Expreſſion proceeds from an alteration which he introduces in the Doctrine.</hi> In fine, he repreſents him as one who is going over to the Sentiments of the new Reformation; or, to uſe his own Expreſſion, <hi>like the Dove which returns to the Ark, not finding where to reſt his foot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An. p. 104, 368.</note>He not only lays to his charge particular Opinions about the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49682:4"/>Merits of Good Works, and the Authority of the Pope; but ſeems ready, if we would conform our ſelves to the Doctrine of the Expoſition, to admit of thoſe two Articles which ſo much perplex thoſe of his Communion.</p>
            <p>There is nothing generally more frequently repeated in his Book,<note place="margin">An. Avert. p. 23, 26. Rep. p, 3. &amp;c.</note> than the reproaches he caſts upon the Author of the Expoſition for deſerting the <hi>Communion of the Church of Rome.</hi> He wiſhes all thoſe of <hi>M. de Condoms</hi> Communion would reduce themſelves to the moderations in this Book,<note place="margin">An. Avert. p. 30.</note> and write conformably to its ſenſe. This would (ſays he a little after) be a happy beginning of a Reformation which might have much more happy conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences.</p>
            <p>Nay more, he takes an advantage from theſe pretended allieva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Theſe Softnings of M. de Condom</hi> (ſays he) <hi>are ſo far from giving us an ill opinion of our Reformation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An. p. 85.</note> 
               <hi>they confirm us that good and moderate Perſon; themſelves condemn (at leaſt a great deal) that we do, and by conſequence in ſome meaſure acknowledge a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to be uſeful and neceſſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſhould have concluded quite otherwiſe. For a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch as theirs is, which tends to a change in Doctrine, ought not to regard thoſe things which are condemned already by a common conſent. But the pretended Reform'd are willing to perſwade themſelves, that the <hi>Honeſt</hi> and <hi>moderate Perſons</hi> in Communion with <hi>Rome,</hi> amongſt which number they allow <hi>M. de Condom</hi> a place, in many things abandon the Sentiments of their Church, and come over as much as they can to the new Reformation.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what they are made to believe by this ſtrange manner of mis-repreſenting the Catholick Doctrine. Being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to that hideous and terrible form in which their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters repreſent it in their Pulpits, they imagine thoſe Catholicks who lay it open in its natural Purity, diſguiſe and alter it: The more juſtly we repreſent it as it is, the leſs are they acquainted with it, and they imagine we are going over to them, when we only diſabuſe them of their falſe preocupations.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, they ſay not always the ſame thing. The <hi>Anonymus,</hi> who accuſes <hi>M. de Condom</hi> of making ſuch conſiderable alterations in the Doctrine of the Church,<note place="margin">p 61, 6</note> tells us <hi>this Expoſition has nothing new in it, but a dextrous and delicate turn,</hi> and in fine nothing but apparent qualifying, which conſiſting only in ſome expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49682:5"/>or in things of ſmall conſequence, gives no body any Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and only raiſes new difficulties, inſtead of reſolving old.</p>
            <p>So that he ſeems to be ſorry for having repreſented the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition as a Book, which made an alteration in the Faith of the Church in all its principal points, not only in the Expreſſions but in the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Let him take it which way he pleaſes. If he continue to think a Book, ſo truly Catholick as the Expoſition, contrary to ſo many important points of the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith, he ſhews himſelf never to have had any thing but falſe Ideas of its Doctrine. And if it be true, that by ſweetning only the expreſſions, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching, as he ſays, matters of ſmall conſequence, the Catholick Doctrine ſeems to him ſo much more tractable, he will in the end find the grounds of it were better then he imagined.</p>
            <p>But the truth of the matter is, <hi>M. de Condom</hi> has not betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his truſt, nor diſſembled the Faith of the Church, in which the Holy Ghoſt has placed him a Biſhop; And the pretended Reform'd could not perſwade themſelves that a Doctrine which already appears leſs ſtrange by the ſole ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of it, and that an Expoſition ſo plain, ſo eaſie, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſhould be that Doctrine which their Miniſters repreſented to them full of Blaſphemy and Idolatrous.</p>
            <p>We ought, no doubt, to give God thanks for ſuch a diſpoſition, becauſe although it ſhew in them a ſtrange prejudice againſt us, yet it gives us hopes they will look upon our Tenets with a more equal temper, when once they are ſatisfied that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of this Treatiſe, which ſeems to them already more pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is the pure Doctrine of the Church. So that we are ſo far from being angry at them for making ſo great a difficulty to to believe us when we propoſe our Faith to them, that we are obliged in Charity to give them Lights ſo clear and evident, that they may not hereafter doubt but it was faithfully expounded to them. The thing ſhews it ſelf, and we need but tell them, that this Treatiſe of the Expoſition, which they believe is contrary <hi>not only to the Common Tenets of the Doctors of the Roman Church, but alſo to the words and Doctrine of the Council,</hi> is approved by the whole Church; and that after having received divers Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Approbation from <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as from other places, it has at laſt been approved by the Pope himſelf in the moſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49682:5"/>expreſs and moſt Authentick manner that could be expected.</p>
            <p>This Book had no ſooner appeared in publick, but the good repute it had throughout <hi>France</hi> was teſtified to the Author by Letters from all ſorts of People, from Lay Perſons, Eccleſiaſticks, Religious, and Doctors, but eſpecially from the moſt Learned Prelates of the Church, whoſe Teſtimonies he could even then have produced, had the Subject been ever ſo little dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or new.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the Pretended Reform'd are apt to believe us in <hi>France</hi> to have particular thoughts and Tenets which approach nearer unto theirs in matters of Faith than the reſt of the Church, and particularly than <hi>Rome:</hi> it is convenient we ſhould let them ſee how matters there were carried on.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as this Treatiſe was come forth, Cardinal <hi>Bouillon</hi> ſent it to Cardinal <hi>Bona,</hi> deſiring him to examine it with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Rigour. Letters could no ſooner return from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> but there came alſo from this Learned and Holy Cardinal, whoſe memory will be perpetuated in the Church with eternal Benediction, that honourable approbation of his, which you will find in the ſequel among the reſt that we ſhall ſpeak of.</p>
            <p>The Book was Printed the firſt time about the end of the year 1671. And this Cardinals anſwer is dated the 26. <hi>January,</hi> 1672.</p>
            <p>Cardinal <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> whoſe death the whole Church doth ſtill regret, writ no leſs favourably concerning it, to <hi>M. l' Abbe de Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geau.</hi> He tells us expreſly, that <hi>M. de Condom</hi> has ſpoken very well of the Popes Authority; and whereas this Abbot had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten him word, that ſome ſcrupulous perſons here apprehended leſt this Expoſition ſhould be looked upon at <hi>Rome,</hi> as one of thoſe Explications of the Council prohibited by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV, he ſhews how ill grounded this ſcruple is. He adds, that he found the Maſter of the Sacred Palace, the Secretary, and the Conſulters of the Congregation <hi>dell' Indice,</hi> all the Cardinals that compoſe it, and in particular the Learned Cardinal <hi>Braneas</hi> Preſident of it, of the ſame opinion, and that they did all of them highly applaud this Treatiſe of the Expoſition. This Letter bears date the 5th of <hi>April,</hi> 1672.</p>
            <p>The Maſter of the Sacred Palace was at time the Reverend Father <hi>Hyacinth Libelli</hi> a famous Divine, whoſe merits and great Learning, raiſed him ſhortly after to the Dignity of Archbiſhop of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49682:6"/>
               <hi>Avignon.</hi> His Letter of the 26th of <hi>April,</hi> 1672 written to his E. the Cardinal <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> ſhews what eſteem he had of this Book; for he tells him, there is not ſo much as the ſhadow of a fault in it, and that if the Author deſire it ſhould be Printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> he will give all the neceſſary permiſſions, without altering the leaſt tittle in it.</p>
            <p>In effect <hi>M. l' Abbe Nazari,</hi> famous for the <hi>Journal des Scavans</hi> which he writes with ſo much elegance and exactneſs, was at that time about an <hi>Italian</hi> Verſion of it, which his E. the Cardinal <hi>d' Eſtrees</hi> cauſed to be reviewed; and did himſelf peruſe ſome of the principal parts, that it might be entirely conformable to the Original.</p>
            <p>The Book had been already done into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by the late Abbot <hi>Montaigue,</hi> whoſe zeal and vertue is known to the whole World, and there wanted not many Teſtimonies to ſhew that his Verſion was well received by all the Catholicks of <hi>England.</hi> This Tranſlation was Printed in the Year, 1672; And in the Year 1675 it was put into <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and Printed at <hi>Rome</hi> by the Printers of the Congregation <hi>de Propaganda Fide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of this Verſion, the Reverend Father, <hi>Porter</hi> of the Holy order of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> and Superiour of the Convent of St. <hi>Iſidorus,</hi> had ſome time before ordered a book called <hi>Securis Evangelica</hi> to be Printed at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, in which a great part of this Treatiſe of the Expoſition was inſerted, to prove the tenets of the Church, when faithfully expounded, to be ſo far from ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Foundations of Faith, that they do eſtabliſh them.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Italian</hi> Verſion went on with an exactneſs which became a Subject of that importance, where one word ill rendred, would ſpoil the whole work; and the Reverend Father <hi>Capiſucchi,</hi> Maſter of the Sacred <hi>Pallace,</hi> Licenſed it to be Printed in the Year 1675 as appears by his anſwer of the 27th of <hi>June</hi> following to <hi>M. de Condoms</hi> Letter of thanks for it.</p>
            <p>This Prelate after having heard from ſeveral parts of <hi>Germany</hi> that this Treatiſe had been well approved of there, received a more ample Teſtimony of it in a Letter of the 27th of <hi>April,</hi> 1673 from the Biſhop and Prince of <hi>Paderho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> then <hi>Coadjutor,</hi> and at preſent Biſhop of <hi>Munſter;</hi> in which that Prelate, whoſe name bears with it his Elogium, ſays, that he took care that this work ſhould be turned into <hi>Latin,</hi> that it might be made Common every where, and eſpecially in <hi>Germany:</hi> but the ſucceeding Wars, or ſome other occupations having hindred the performance of it,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49682:6"/>the Biſhop of <hi>Caſtory Apoſtolical Vicar</hi> in the United Provinces was deſirous that a <hi>Latin</hi> Verſion, which the Author himſelf had examined, might be made publick, and accordingly it was Printed at <hi>Antwerp</hi> in the Year 1678.</p>
            <p>Not long after in the ſame year, by the ſame Biſhops order, this Treatiſe was again Printed at <hi>Antwerp</hi> in <hi>Dutch,</hi> with the Approbation of the Ordinary, and the Doctors in thoſe parts, ſo much did this Prelate, who compoſes ſuch excellent things himſelf, judge this to be profitable for the inſtruction of his People.</p>
            <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Strasbourgh,</hi> who notwithſtanding the miſcries of War, was no leſs careful of his Flock, reſolved, about the ſame time, to procure that this Book might be turned into High Dutch, and publiſhed with a Paſtoral Letter to all thoſe of his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; and having advertiſed the Pope of his deſign, his Holineſs cauſed him to be informed, that he knew the Book long before; and that as he had heard from all parts it was the occaſion of many Converſions, ſo the tranſlation of it could not but be advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to his People.</p>
            <p>About this time the <hi>Italian</hi> Verſion was finiſhed with all the exactneſs and elegancy poſſible. Monſieur <hi>l' Abbe Nazari</hi> dedicated it to the Cardinals of the Congregation <hi>de propaganda ſide,</hi> by whoſe order it was printed the ſame Year 1678. by the Printers belonging to that Congregation.</p>
            <p>In the front of this Verſion was placed the Cardinal <hi>Bona</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Coppy of which was fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Hands of his Secretary, as alſo the Approbations of <hi>M. l' Abbe Ricci,</hi> Conſultor of the Holy Office; of the Reverend Father <hi>M. Laurence Brancati de Laurea,</hi> Religious of the Order of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> Conſultor and Qualificator of the Holy Office, and Bibliothecarian of the <hi>Vati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can;</hi> and of <hi>M. L' Abbe Gradi</hi> Conſultor of the Congregation <hi>Dell' Indice,</hi> and Bibliothecarian of the <hi>Vatican:</hi> that is, by the chief men in <hi>Rome</hi> for Piety and Learning.</p>
            <p>This Book was preſented to the Pope, as the Latin Tranſlation had been before. And he had the goodneſs to order <hi>M. l' Abbe de St. Luke</hi> to write to the Author, and to let him know that he was ſatisfied with it; which he alſo repeated ſeveral times to the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour.</p>
            <p>The Author, who thought he had nothing more to wiſh for after ſuch an Approbation, gave, with a profound reſpect, his moſt humble thanks to the Pope, in a Letter dated <hi>Nov.</hi> 22. 1678.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49682:7"/>In anſwer to which, he received a Breve from his Holineſs of the Fourth of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1679, which contains ſuch an expreſs approbation of this Book, that it cannot be hereafter doubted, but it main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the pure Doctrine of the Church, and of the Apoſtolick See.</p>
            <p>After this approbation, I needed not to have mentioned any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but I was willing to ſhew how this Book, which was threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Miniſters with ſuch oppoſition in the Church, and which they imagined was ſo contrary to her common Doctrine, has naturally (as I may ſay) paſſed through all the degrees of Approbation, till it came to that of the Pope himſelf, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of the Pretended Reformed Religion, may at preſent ſee how they were impoſed upon,<note place="margin">An. Avert. p. 23.</note> when they were told, <hi>The Perſon was known, and that a Catholick too, who writ againſt this Expoſition of</hi> M. de Condom. It would certainly be a ſtrange thing, this good Catholick, unknown to all others of that Religion, ſhould make the Enemies of the Church his only Confidents in a Work which he deſigned againſt a Biſhop of his own Communion. But this Imaginary Writer makes the World ſtay too long, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reform'd are too credulous, if they ſuffer themſelves hereafter to be amuſed by ſuch like Promiſes.</p>
            <p>Thus one of the neceſſary Queſtions to be anſwered in vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Expoſition is entirely diſpatch'd. We need not now go about to refute thoſe Miniſters who held the Doctrine of the Expoſition not to be that of the Church. Time and Truth have ſo refuted their allegations, that no room is left for a reply.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Nog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ier</hi> would firſt hear the Oracle of <hi>Rome</hi> ſpeak, before he would admit <hi>M. de Condom</hi> to have rightly explicated the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock Faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 41.</note> 
               <hi>I give no credit</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to thoſe Approbations which theſe Biſhops give in Writing. Other Doctors want not the like Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations, and after all, the Oracle of</hi> Rome <hi>muſt ſpeak in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith.</hi> The <hi>Anonymus</hi> was of the ſame mind, and both of them ſuppoſed nothing more could be ſaid in this matter againſt <hi>M. de Condom,</hi> if once this Oracle had but ſpoken. This Oracle has now ſpoken, this Oracle, I ſay, which the whole Catholick Church hearkned to with ſo much reſpect in the very origine of Chriſtianity; and the anſwer it has given, has ſhewn what this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late had ſaid, hath nothing new, or to be ſuſpected in it, nothing in a word, which is not receiv'd throughout the whole Church.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49682:7"/>
Nay, this Queſtion being anſwered, all the others are in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner inſenſibly diſpatcht.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>de Condom</hi> held, the Catholick Doctrine was never right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood by the pretended Reform'd; and that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of their Separation had magnified the Objects to render them odious. What he ſaid, appears now moſt certain, ſeeing it is manifeſt on the one ſide, the Expoſition propoſes to them the Catholick Faith, in its Purity; and on the other, that it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed leſs ſtrange to them than they thought it was.</p>
            <p>But if they find their Pretended Reformers, to the end they might animate them againſt that Church, in which their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors ſerved God, and in which they themſelves received Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, were forced to fly to thoſe Calumnies which we ſee now are not maintainable, how can they diſpence with themſelves if they ſearch not a new? And why are they not afraid to perſiſt in a Schiſm, which is manifeſtly founded upon falſe Principles, in even the moſt principal points?</p>
            <p>They believ'd for example, they had good grounds to ſeparate from the Church, under pretence, that whilſt ſhe taught the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of good Works, ſhe deſtroyed Free Juſtification,<note place="margin">Gratuite.</note> and that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence which a Chriſtian ought to have in <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> only.</p>
            <p>Their breach was principally founded upon this Article.<note place="margin">An. p. 86.</note> The <hi>Anonymus</hi> thinks it enough to ſay, <hi>The Article concerning Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is one of the chief, that gave occaſion to the Reformation.</hi> But M. <hi>Noguiers</hi> ſpeaks more plainly.<note place="margin">Nog. p. 83.</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>who were the Authors of our Reformation had reaſon to propoſe the Article of Juſtification, as the moſt principal of the reſt, and the moſt Eſſential Foundation of their ſeparating.</hi> At preſent then, ſeeing <hi>M. de Condom</hi> tells them, together with the whole Church,<note place="margin">Expoſ. p. 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>That ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves we cannot have Life, but in Jeſus Chriſt, in whom alone ſhe puts all her Hope: That ſhe asks all things, hopes all things, and gives thanks for all things, through our Lord JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST: and in fine, that ſhe places all the hopes of Salvation on him:</hi> What would they have more.</p>
            <p>The Church tells us,<note place="margin">Expoſ. p. 15.</note> 
               <hi>That all our Sins ars pardon'd by pure Mercy through JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, That we owe that Juſtice which is in us, by the Holy Ghoſt, to his free undeſerved liberality; and that all our good Works which we do, are ſo many gifts of his Grace.</hi> The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Expoſition, who teaches this Doctrine, does not teach it as his own; God forbid.<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 15.</note> He teaches it as the clear and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49682:8"/>Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and the Pope approves his Book. After this ſhall it be again ſaid, That the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church overthrow Free Juſtification, and that truſt which the Faithful ought to repoſe in Jeſus Chriſt alone. Is not this unſufferable? And if we ſhould hold our Tongues would not the Stones cry aloud, and proclaim us injur'd?</p>
            <p>It muſt be alſo granted, as it was taken notice of in the Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Ex. p, 15.</note> that thoſe Diſputes which the Pretended Reform'd have raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon ſo capital a Point, are almoſt brought to nothing, not to ſay wholly refuted. No body will doubt of it, if they conſider what the <hi>Anonymus</hi> has writ concerning the merit of Good Works with the approbation of four Miniſters of <hi>Charenton. We acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> (ſays he) <hi>as in Juſtice we muſt</hi> M. de Condom, <hi>and thoſe of the</hi> Roman Church,<note place="margin">An. p. 104.</note> 
               <hi>who hold the most Orthodox Opinions concerning Grace, expreſs themſelves almost in all things as we do. We agree with them in the main.</hi> But ſince he promiſed us ſo much Juſtice, he ought to have acknowledged, that <hi>M. de Condom,</hi> whom he makes here to be of a particular Sect, has not ſaid one word concerning the merit of Good Works, which is not taken from the Council.<note place="margin">Expoſ. p. 13, 14, 15.</note> He ſaid, <hi>Eternal Life ought to be propoſed to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, both as a Grace which is mercifully promiſed to them by the means of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and as a Recompence which is faithfully rendred to their good Works, and to their merits, in virtue of that Promiſe.</hi> He ſaid, <hi>That Merits are the gifts of God.</hi> He ſaid, <hi>We can do nothing of our ſelves, but that we can do all things with him who ſtrengthens us, and that our whole confidence is in JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi> And the reſt, which you may ſee in their proper place. By this means it is he has ſatisfied the Pretended Reform'd, and made them ſay, they agree with him in <hi>the main.</hi> Seeing therefore theſe Propoſitions are taken word by word from the Council, they cannot hereafter but acknowledge the <hi>Principal</hi> Subject of their complaints to be taken away, by the ſole propoſing the Decrees and proper Terms of a Council ſo much hated and blamed amongſt them.</p>
            <p>What is it offends them moſt in the Satisfactions which the Church exacts from the Faithful, but only that they think <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> looks upon thoſe of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> as unſufficient? Will they deny their Catechiſms, and Confeſſions of Faith are not ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon this foundation? What will they now ſay, when the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Expoſition tells them, with the whole Church. <hi>That
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49682:8"/>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Expoſ. p. 16. &amp; ſeq.</note> 
               <hi>God and Man was ſolely capable by the infinite Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Perſon, to offer up to God a ſufficient Satisfaction for our Sins: That this Satisfaction is infinite; That our Saviour has payed the entire Price of our Redemption; That nothing is wanting to this Price, ſeeing it is infinite; and that the Puniſhments reſerv'd, ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Penance, come not from any defect in the Payment, but from a certain Order, which he has eſtabliſhed to reſtrain us, by juſt fears, and by a ſaving Diſcipline?</hi> Theſe and all thoſe other Expreſſions which make the <hi>Anonymus</hi> ſay, this Author <hi>extenuates</hi> the Doctrine of Satisfaction, and <hi>returns like the Dove to the Ark,</hi> are the pure Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Church, and of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for ſuch by the Pope himſelf. Why therefore will they make People believe the Church looks upon that as an aid to the Satisfactions of Jeſus Chriſt, which ſhe propoſes as a means only to apply it? And with what ſecurity of Conſcience could the Pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reform'd, upon ſuch falſe ſuppoſitions, violate that Holy unity, which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> has ſo much recommended to his Church.</p>
            <p>They look upon our Sacrifice of the Altar with Horrour, as if <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> were again put to Death upon it.<note place="margin">Epoſ. p. 25.</note> What has the Author of the Expoſition done to diminiſh this horrour ſo unjuſt, but only repreſented the Doctrine of the Church faithfully. He has told them this Sacrifice is of ſuch a nature, that it admits only a myſtical and Spiritual Death of our adorable Victim, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains always impaſſible and immortal; and is ſo far from dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the infinite Perfection of the Sacrifice of the Croſs, <hi>It is eſtabliſhed only to celebrate the remembrance of it, and to apply the Vertue.</hi> The <hi>Anonymus</hi> aſſures us upon this account, that <hi>M. de Condom,</hi> minces the Doctrine of the Catholick Church: And <hi>M. Noguier</hi> alſo aſſures us, he has not expoſed the Truth.<note place="margin">Nog. p. 286. Exp. p. 36. An. p. 61. An. p. 24.</note> And yet he has only followed the Doctrine of the Council, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Terms he has made uſe of; and the whole Church approves his Expoſition. Who does not therefore perceive how this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine appears to the Pretended Reform'd more moderate and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, only becauſe they do not find thoſe Monſters in it, which they imagine to themſelves?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Anonymus</hi> himſelf tells us,<note place="margin">Rep. p. 24, 35.</note> 
               <hi>The Article of Invocation of Saints is one of the moſt Eſſential in Religion.</hi> It is alſo one of thoſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>M. de Condom</hi> ſeems to him <hi>chiefly to ſoften the Doctrine of his Church;</hi> for he accuſes him of it no leſs than three times. But what has <hi>M. de Condom</hi> ſaid? the ſame that the Catechiſm of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49682:9"/>Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſaid, the ſame that the Council it ſelf, and the Confeſſion of Faith drawn from it has ſaid, and the ſame which all Catholicks ſay:<note place="margin">Epoſ. p. 6. ſequ.</note> 
               <hi>That the Saints offer their Prayers for us.</hi> This is what the Confeſſion of Faith ſays, that they offer them by <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST;</hi> this is what the Council ſays, in a word, That we pray to them with the ſame Mind we pray to <hi>our Brethren, who are upon Earth with us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Expoſ. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>that is, to Pray with us, and for us, to our common Maſter, in the name of our common Mediator, who is JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi> Behold what <hi>Mide Condom</hi> has extracted out of the Council, out of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, and out of all the publick acts of the Church, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon his Doctrine has been ſo much approved.</p>
            <p>This anſwer is ſufficient to ruin the very Grounds of that horrour, which the Pretended Reform'd have conceived againſt our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>Their Catechiſm accuſes us of <hi>Idolatry, becauſe by that recourſe we have to Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Catech. dim. 34.</note> 
               <hi>we place one part of our Truſt in them, and give to them what God has reſerv'd to himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But on the contrary, it appears, when we pray to Saints, we Pray to them only to pray for us; a kind of Prayer, which by its own Nature, is ſo far from being reſerved by an independent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to himſelf, it can never be addreſs'd to him.</p>
            <p>And if this form of Prayer, <hi>Pray for us,</hi> diminiſhed the truſt we have in God, it would be no leſs Condemnable to uſe it to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, than to the dead;<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.25.2, 3.1.</note> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have ſaid ſo often. <hi>Brethren pray for us.</hi> The whole Scripture is full of Prayers of this Nature.<note place="margin">Heb. 13.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But (ſays their Confeſſion of Faith) this is to overthrow the Mediation of <hi>J. C. Who commands us to retire our ſelves in private,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conf. Art. 24.</note> 
               <hi>and to pray to his Father in his Name.</hi> How can any one imagine this, ſeeing the Saints, who are in Heaven, no more than the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful upon Earth, make interceſſions by, and through themſelves, or in their own Names;<note place="margin">Ep. p. 6.</note> but in the Name of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> as all Catholicks teach with the Council?</p>
            <p>Thus the Catholick Church has only to declare, as ſhe does, her intention never was to demand any thing of the Saints, but their humble Prayers in the name of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> of Nature with thoſe the Faithful offer up for one another upon Earth, theſe few Words will convince for ever the pretendedly Reform'd, that they have born to her a hatred moſt unjuſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49682:9"/>
But <hi>M: Noguier</hi> declares, <hi>Let M. de Candom ſay what he will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nog. p. 54.</note> 
               <hi>he will never be perſwaded, the</hi> Roman <hi>Church has no other Intention (when ſhe tells us, it is proſitable to invocate the Saints) but that we ſhould aſk them the aſſiſtance of their Prayers; as we do thoſe of the Faithful, who live amongſt us.</hi> But what will he ſay, now he ſees the <hi>Roman</hi> Church ſo viſibly approve what <hi>M. de Condom</hi> had in effect only gathered from the univerſal belief of thoſe in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with her? But <hi>why then,</hi> adds <hi>M. Noguier,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nog. p. 57.</note> 
               <hi>Do Catholicks aſk not only the Prayers, but the Aid, Protection, and Succour of the bleſſed Virgin, and of the Saints?</hi> As if that were not a kind of <hi>Aid, Succour, and Protection,</hi> to recommend the miſerable to him, who alone can comfort them. Such is the Protection we may receive from the bleſſed Virgin and from the Saints. It is not a ſmall Succour to be aided by their Prayers, ſeeing they are at the ſame time ſo humble, ſo pleaſing, and ſo efficatious. But why ſhould we argue about words, where the thing is ſo evident? The Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion produces to theſe Miniſters moſt certain Teſtimonies, by which it is manifeſt,<note place="margin">Expoſ. p. 7.</note> 
               <hi>that in what Terms ſoever the Prayers we offer to the Saints be Couched, the Intention of the Church, and of the Faithful; always reduces them to this Form, PRAY FOR <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> No matter for that, the Miniſters <hi>will never believe it.</hi> They muſt then raiſe out of their Catechiſm, and their Confeſſion of Faith, theſe accuſations of Idolatry, with which they are filled; they muſt retrench in their Sermons, ſo many bloody Invectives, which have no other Grounds, and this they cannot reſolve of; and let us make what Declarations we can of our Minds, they will neither believe the Council, not its Catechiſm, nor our Confeſſion of Faith, nor the Biſhops, nor the Pope himſelf.</p>
            <p>It is not neceſſary to repeat here what is ſaid in the Expoſition as to other objections,<note place="margin">Exp. p. 8.</note> and principally as to that where they accuſe the Church of attributing to Saints a divine Knowledge and Power, whilſt ſhe teaches, they can neither know, nor do any thing of themſelves.</p>
            <p>But the accuſation of Idolatry has another Foundation, which they accuſe <hi>M. de Condom to have palliated</hi> as well as the others. And it is the Article concerning Images,<note place="margin">An. Av. p. 24.</note> where nevertheleſs he has ſearched no other Palliations, but to expoſe faithfully the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church.<note place="margin">Rep. p. 65.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There needs no more than this to make the very Suſpition of Idolatry to vaniſh, according to the Principles of the Pretended
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49682:10"/>Reform'd; and they need only in this compare the Doctrine of their own Catechiſm with that of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Expoſition.</p>
            <p>Their Catechiſm upon this Commandment.<note place="margin">Dim. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any Graven Image,</hi> Asks whether God <hi>forbids the making of any Image?</hi> And the anſwer is, <hi>No, but that God forbids only the making of any Image whereby to repreſent God or to adore it.</hi> Behold the two things which they think forbidden in this Precept of the Decalogue.</p>
            <p>It may be they will do us the Juſtice to believe we do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to repreſent God, and that if they ſee in ſome Pictures God the Father Painted in that form which he was pleaſed ſo often to appear in to his Prophets, we pretend no more to derogate from his Inviſibile and Spiritual Nature, than he himſelf when he exhibited himſelf under that form. The Council explicates ſufficiently to them upon this account,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>that we pretend not thereby to repreſent or expreſs the Divinity, or to give it any Colours;</hi> and I think I ſhould do them an injury in proceeding to a clearer Proof.</p>
            <p>Let us paſs to the ſecond part of their Doctrine, and let us learn from their Catechiſms <hi>what form of Adoration is condemned. To Proſtrate ones ſelf,</hi> ſays the Anſwer, <hi>before an Image, to pray to it, to how the Knee before it, or ſhew ſome other ſign of reverence, as if God exhibited himſelf there to us.</hi> This is in effect the Errour of the Gentiles, and the proper Character of Idolatry. But they who believe,<note place="margin">Expoſ. p. 9, 10, 11.</note> with the Council, <hi>That Images have neither Divinity nor Vertue in them, for which they ought to be reverenced,</hi> and who place all the benefit, in their recalling the Originals to our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, do not believe that God in them <hi>exhibits himſelf to them.</hi> It is not therefore Idolatry, by the conſent of the Pretended Reform'd, and according to the proper Definition of their Catechiſm.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Anonymus</hi> ſeems to have been ſenſible of this Truth in that place, where objecting this Commandment of the Decalogue he ſays,<note place="margin">P. 67.</note> that God <hi>forbids to make Images, and to worſhip them.</hi> He is in the right. The words of the Precept are expreſs, and the Images there ſpoken of are thoſe which are forbidden to <hi>to be made</hi> as well as to be <hi>worſhiped:</hi> That is to ſay, according to the explication of his Catechiſm, <hi>thoſe which are made to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent God, and thoſe which are made to ſhow him preſent,</hi> and which are worſhipped with the ſame intention as full of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49682:10"/>We neither make nor ſuffer any of this nature. We do not worſhip Images; God forbid: but we make uſe of Images, to put us in mind of the Originals. Our Council, ſo odious to the pretended Reform'd Church, teaches us no other uſe of them: Is this then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make them ſay, as that Church doth in her own Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>that all ſorts of Idolatry are in vogue in the Roman Church?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Art. 28.</note> Is it for this that her Diſcipline calls us <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and our Religion <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſc. art. 11.13. Art. 5.2.</note> Without doubt they repreſent to themſelves other things than our Doctrine, when they give us the name of Gentiles: They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve we follow their abominable Errors, and that we believe as they did, that God ſhews himſelf to us in thoſe Images.</p>
            <p>Had it not been for theſe mortal Prejudices, had it not been for I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas which they frame to themſelves of the ſentiments of the Church, Chriſtians could never have imagined it ſo deteſtable a crime to kiſs the Croſs in remembrance of him who bore our Iniquities upon the wood, nor that ſo ſimple and natural a demonſtration of thoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of tenderneſs, which that Pious Object excites in our hearts ought to make us regarded as if we Adored <hi>Baal,</hi> or the Golden Galves of <hi>Samaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During this ſtrange preocupation of the Pretended Reform'd, this Treatiſe of the Expoſition might well appear to them (which really in effect it did) a Book full of Artifice, which did nothing but extenuate the Sentiments of Catholicks. But now when they ſee clearly: all the Artifice of this Book is to ſeparate the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which they have imputed to the Church, from thoſe which ſhe profeſſes, that all the mitigations he makes in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is that he has taken off that hidious Maſque which the Miniſters had put upon it: let them confeſs this Church was not worthy of ſo much horror, as they had for her, and that at leaſt ſhe deſerves to be heard.</p>
            <p>Neither the Pope, nor the Sea Apoſtolick ought to be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after accuſed of diminſhing that adoration which is due to God, nor that confidence which a Chriſtian ought to eſtabliſh in his ſole goodneſs through our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſince they ſee, without further ſearch, this Treatiſe of the Expoſition, which is made only to explicate theſe two Truths, has received at <hi>Rome</hi> and from the Pope himſelf ſo Authentick an Approbation.</p>
            <p>After this they will certainly be aſhamed of that Title which they give the Pope. No one can think on it without horrour, nor hear without aſtoniſhment, that the Pretended Reform'd,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49682:11"/>who boaſt to follow Scripture word for word, when the Apoſtle St. <hi>John,</hi> who has alone named Antichriſt, tells us three or four times that <hi>Antichriſt is he who denies that JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST is come in fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Joh. 1.7. 1 Joh. 2.22.4.3.</note> dare ſo much as think that he, who teaches ſo fully the Myſtery of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> that is to ſay, his Divinity, his Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the ſuperbundance of his Merits, the neceſſity of his Grace, and that abſolute confidence we muſt have in it, ſhould neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs be that Antichriſt deſcribed by the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>But it is objected againſt the Popes,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.3.4.</note> that they <hi>are: that wicked Perſon, that man of Iniquity who has ſeated himſelf in the Temple of God; and makes himſelf adored as God;</hi> They who confeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not only mortal men, but ſinners, who pray every day with the reſt of the Faithful, <hi>forgive us our offences,</hi> and who never approach the Altar without Confeſſing of their ſins, and without ſaying in the moſt eſſential part of the Holy Sacrifice, they hope for eternal life, not by their own Merits, but through the Bounty of God in the name of our Lord <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis true they maintain that Primacy which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> has given them in the Perſon of St. <hi>Peter;</hi> but it is by That they advance the Work of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> himſelf, the Work of Charity and Concord, which would never have been perfectly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, if the Univerſal Church and all the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Order had not one head of Eccleſiaſtical Gover ment upon Earth, to make the Members act in concurrence, and accompliſh in the whole Body the Myſtery of Unity ſo much recommended by the Son of God. It is juſt as much as nothing to anſwer, that the Church has her true Head in Heaven, who Unites her by animating her with his Holy Spirit: who doubts of it! But who does not know this Holy Spirit, who diſpoſes all things with as much ſweetneſs as efficacy, knows alſo how to prepare exteriour means pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to his deſigns? The Holy Ghoſt both teaches and governs us interiourly: therefore he eſtabliſhes Paſtors and Teachers to Act exterourly. The Holy Ghoſt Unites the Body of the Church and the Eccleſiaſtical Government: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is he places at the head a common Father, and a principal diſpoſer who may Govern the whole Family of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi> We will call to witneſs the Conſciences of thoſe of the Pretended Reform'd Religion, In this unfortunate age when ſo many wicked Sects endeavour by little and little to undermine the Foundations
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49682:11"/>of Chriſtianity, and believe it enough only to name <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> to introduce indifferency in Religion, and manifeſt impiety into the boſom of the Church, Who ſees not the neceſſity of a Paſtor, who may watch over his flock, and, authorized from above, encite all others whoſe vigilance might ſlacken? Let them in reality tell us, if it be not the <hi>Seconians,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> the <hi>Independants,</hi> thoſe who under the name of Chriſtian Liberty would eſtabliſh indifferency in Religions, and ſo many other pernicious Sects, which they condemn as well as we, who fly with the greateſt impetuoſity againſt St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, and cry loudeſt that his Authority is Tyrannical? I do not wonder at it: thoſe who would divide the Church, or ſurpriſe her, fear nothing more than to ſee her march againſt them like a well ranged Army under one head. Let us not raiſe a quarrel with any, let us only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect whence come thoſe Books, wherein theſe dangerous Licenſes, and Antichriſtian Doctrines are taught: at leaſt none can deny but the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the very Conſtitution of it, is incompatible with theſe Novelties; and if we could not know by the Goſpel that the Primacy of this See is neceſſary for us, Experience it ſelf would convince us of it. Moreover, We muſt not be aſtoniſhed if this Author of the Expoſition, who places the eſſential Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of this See in thoſe things wherein all Catholic Schools agree, hath been approved without difficulty. The Chair of St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtands in need of no diſputing; what all Catholics ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge without conteſtation, ſuffices to maintain that Power which was given to it for edification, and not for deſtruction. The Pretended Reform'd ſhould hereafter give way no more to thoſe vain Phantoms with which they are frighted. What does it profit them to ſearch in Hiſtories for the Vices of Popes? when, if what they meet with there ſhould be true, does the Vices of men deſtroy the inſtitution of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> and the Priviledge of St. <hi>Peter?</hi> ſhall the Church riſe in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt a Power which maintains her Unity, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that ſome have abus'd it? Chriſtians are accuſtomed to reaſon upon higher and more true Principles, and know that God is able to maintain his works in the midſt of all the evils which accompany humane frailty.</p>
            <p>We do then Conjure theſe of the Pretended Reform'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by that Charity, which is God himſelf, by the name of Chriſtian, which is common to us both, not to judge of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49682:12"/>of our Church, by what they hear in their Sermons or read in their Books, where many times the heat of diſpute, and Prevention (not to mention any other) make things frequently otherwiſe repreſented then they are; but to hearken to this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Catholic Doctrine. It is a work in reality, which conſiſts not ſo much in diſputing, as in explicating clearly our belief; In which to ſee how plainly the Author has proceeded, we need only conſider his deſign.</p>
            <p>He promiſed in the very beginning,
<list>
                  <item>1. To propoſe the true Tenets of the Catholic Church,<note place="margin">Exp. p. 2.</note> and <hi>to diſtinguiſh them from thoſe which are falſely imputed to her</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. To the end no one ſhould doubt but that he faithfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the true Sentiments of the Church,<note place="margin">Exp. p. 2.</note> he promiſed to take them <hi>from the Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> where the Church has ſpoken deciſively upon the things in queſtion.</item>
                  <item>3. He promiſed to propoſe to the Pretended Reform'd not all points in general,<note place="margin">Exp. p. 2.</note> but <hi>thoſe which cauſed the greateſt ſeparation betwixt them and us,</hi> and, to ſpeak properly, thoſe which they made the occaſions of their breach.</item>
                  <item>4. He promiſed that what he <hi>ſaid to make the deciſions of the Council more intelligible,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exp. p. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhould be approved of in the Church, and manifeſtly conformable to the Doctrine of the ſame Council.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All this is plain and juſt. And, in the firſt place, no body can think it ſtrange we ſhould diſtinguiſh the Churches Tenets <hi>from thoſe which are falſely imputed to her.</hi> When Perſons are animated beyond meaſure, for want of a right underſtanding, and when ſtrange prejudices move great diſputes, there is nothing more natural, nothing more charitable, then to explicate matters clearly. The Holy Fathers practiſed a way fraudleſs and calm like this, to ſet men right again. Whilſt the <hi>Arians</hi> and <hi>Semi-Arians</hi> decryed the Symbol of <hi>Nice,</hi> and the Conſubſtantiality of the Son, by the falſe Ideas they fixed upon them, <hi>St. Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> and <hi>St. Hilarius,</hi> the two moſt illuſtrious defenders of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith, repreſented to them the true ſenſe of the Councils: and <hi>St. Hilarius</hi> ſaid to them:<note place="margin">S. Hil. lib. de ſyn.</note> 
               <hi>Let us both together condemn falſe Interpretations, but not deſtroy the certainty of Faith</hi>—The Word <hi>Conſubſtantial may be miſ-underſtood: let us reſolve how we may rightly underſtand it</hi>—<hi>We may lay down the true ſtate of Faith betwixt us, if we do not overthrow what has been rightly eſtabliſhed, but remover miſ-underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49682:12"/>
It is Charity it ſelf which dictates ſuch words, and ſuggeſts ſuch means to reunite our minds. We may ſay the ſame to theſe of the Pretended Reform'd Religion: If the Merit of Good Works, if Prayers addreſſed to Saints, if the Euchariſt, if the humble ſatisfactions of Penitents, who endeavour to appeaſe the wrath of God in voluntarily revenging upon themſelves by La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious Exerciſes his offended Juſtice, if the Terms we uſe of a Tradition which claims its Origin from the firſt Ages, for want of being rightly underſtood offend you; The Author of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition offers himſelf to give you the plain and natural explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, which the Church has always faithfully conſerv'd. He ſays nothing of his own, he alledges not particular Authors; and to the end he may not be ſuſpected of changing the Tenets of the Church, he uſes the proper Terms of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> where ſhe has explicated her ſelf upon theſe matters in queſtion: what can there be more rational?</p>
            <p>This was the ſecond thing he promiſed, and he has in this only followed the Example of the Pretended Reform'd. They complain as well as we, their Doctrines are not rightly underſtood; and the means they propoſe to come to a true knowledge of them, is not different from that which <hi>M. de Condom</hi> makes uſe of. Their Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> requires that <hi>none judge of the Faith of their Churches from Calumnies picked up here and there,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concluſio Synodi Dordrac. in Syntag. Confeſſ. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei edit. <hi>Genev. p. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or paſſages of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Authors, which are often falſely cited, or wreſted to a ſenſe contrary to their Intentions; but from the Confeſſions of Faith of their Churches, and from the Declaration of their Orthodox Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine unanimouſly made in this Synod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Faith then of a Church muſt be learnt from its publick De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions, and not from Private Authors, who may be falſely quoted, miſ-underſtood, and may alſo themſelves miſ-explicate the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Religion. Upon which account it will be only neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that, to expound ours to the Pretended Reform'd, we produce the Deciſions of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know the very name of this Council offends, thoſe of the Reformation, and the <hi>Anonymus</hi> often ſhews his ill humour againſt it. But what do his Invectives avail him? We go not here about to juſtifie the Council: It ſuffices for this Author of the Expoſition, that the Doctrine of this Council is univerſally recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, without Conteſtation, through the whole Catholic Church, and that ſhe admits of no other Deciſions, in theſe matters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, but of this Council.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49682:13"/>
The Pretended Reform'd have always endeavoured to have theſe Deciſions thought ambiguous, and the <hi>Anonymus</hi> reproaches us alſo with their being capable of a <hi>double or triple ſenſe.</hi> Thoſe who have not read this Council,<note place="margin">An. p. 11.12.</note> unleſs it were in the Invectives of their Miniſters, and in the Hiſtory of <hi>Fa. Paul,</hi> the declared Enemy of it, believe them ſuch: but one word will ſatisfie them. It is very true, there was ſome Points the Council would not decide, and they were thoſe concerning which there was no ſettled Tradition, and which were diſputed of in the Schools; It was but reaſonable they ſhould be left undecided: but for thoſe it has decided, it has ſpoken ſo preciſely, that amongſt ſo many Decrees of this Council produced in the Expoſition, the <hi>Anonymus</hi> could not find ſo much as one, in which there was this double or triple ſence he objects againſt us.</p>
            <p>In effect, It is but reading them, and one ſhall ſee they have not any ambiguity, and that it is impoſſible for men to expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate themſelves more clearly.</p>
            <p>We may put the Expoſition it ſelf to the ſame Teſt, and judge by that, whether the <hi>Anonymus</hi> had reaſon to upbraid the Author of this Expoſition with <hi>thoſe rambling and general Terms in which</hi> (ſays he) <hi>he entanglingly wraps up the most difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Avert. p. 25.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Rep. p. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The third thing the Author of the Expoſition promiſed, was to treat of thoſe matters <hi>which gave occaſion to the Separation.</hi> This is preciſely what ought to be done. There is no one who knows not that in diſputes there are always ſome certain princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal points upon which mens minds are fixed. It is to theſe a Perſon muſt apply himſelf who would make it his buſineſs to end or appeaſe thoſe conteſts. Thus did the Author of the Expoſition, who immediately declared to the Pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, that he would expound to them thoſe points <hi>from which they took the Subject of their ſeparation.</hi> And to the end there ſhould be no ſurprize,<note place="margin">Exp. p. 2.</note> he again declares the ſame at the end, <hi>that to keep himſelf fixed to what is principal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exp. p. 50.</note> 
               <hi>he omitted ſome queſtions which they of the Pretended Reform'd Religion did not look upon as a lawful Subject of ſeparation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He has kept his word moſt faithfully, and the Titles alone of the Expoſition will make it appear, he has not omitted any one of thoſe principal Articles.</p>
            <p>So that the <hi>Anonymus</hi> ſhould not have ſaid that <hi>M. de Condom has
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49682:13"/>ſome ſelect Terms to avoid the difficulties which give him the moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Avert. p. 22.</note> 
               <hi>that he leaves many queſtions untouched, and makes haſt to that of the Euchariſt, where he thought he could enlarge himſelf with leſs diſadvantage.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Repl. p. 168.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What an Idea would he give us of this Book of the Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! but it deſtroys it ſelf. Every one ſees it was <hi>M. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>'s buſineſs to enlarge himſelf upon that point of the Euchariſt, not becauſe he thought he could do it <hi>with leſs diſadvantage,</hi> but becauſe this point is in reality the moſt difficult, and full of great queſtions. So that it will appear he has treated theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with leſs or greater ſcope, according as they appear'd leſs or more embroiling, not to him, but to thoſe, for whom he writes. And if it be true that <hi>he lays aſide thoſe difficulties which give him the moſt trouble,</hi> it muſt be allow'd, thoſe which give him the leaſt, are in reality thoſe which are the moſt eſſential, and thoſe in which the Pretended Reform'd always thought themſelves the moſt ſecure. He has treated of the worſhip due to God, of Prayers to Saints, of the honour we render to them, as alſo to their Images and Reliques. He has ſpoken of juſtifying Grace, of the Merit of Good Works, of the neceſſity of Works, of Satisfaction, of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, of Indulgences, of Sacramental Confeſſion and Abſolution, of the Real Preſence of the Body and Blood of our Saviour in the Euchariſt, of that Adoration which is therein due to him, of Tranſubſtantiation, and the Sacrifice of the Altar, of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion under one Species, of the Authority of Tradition and that of the Church, of the Divine Inſtitution of the Popes Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, where he has in one word explained what is to be believed of Epiſcopacy. He has expounded all theſe difficulties, and there needs only a little honeſty to grant that he has been ſo far from avoiding difficulties, as the <hi>Anonymus</hi> would have it thought, that he has principally applied himſelf to thoſe which the Pretended Reform'd find the greateſt. The <hi>Anonymus</hi> himſelf tells us <hi>the Invocation of Saints is one of the moſt eſſential Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Religion;</hi> and at the ſame time he adds,<note place="margin">P. 61.</note> 
               <hi>this is one of thoſe upon which</hi> M. de Condom <hi>has been most prolix.</hi> What points are more exactly treated in the Expoſition than thoſe of the Euchariſt and the Sacrifice, that of Images, of Merit, of Good works, of Satisfaction? And is it not in theſe the Pretended Reform'd find the greateſt difficulties? In fine, we will ask even themſelves, whether it be not true, that if they were ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49682:14"/>in all thoſe points treated of in the Expoſition, they would no longer heſitate to embrace the Faith of the Church? It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore certain, the Author has treated all thoſe Capital points upon which both of us agree the greateſt difficulties move. Nay more, he has always fixed himſelf to the principal knot of the difficulty, ſeeing he applies himſelf chiefly, according to his firſt promiſe, to thoſe parts where the Catholic Doctrine is accuſed to ſtrike at the Foundations of Faith and Chriſtian Piety. It is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to avoid difficulties, he has left ſome queſtions untouched which are but Conſequences and fuller Explications of thoſe which he has handled; or at leaſt, are ſuch as diſturb no body. But, on the contrary, he has done it to the end he might apply himſelf with leſs diſtraction to the chief difficulties upon which depend the Deciſion of our Controverſies.</p>
            <p>The Author of the Expoſition has been no leſs Faithful in performance of his fourth promiſe, which was to affirm nothing to make the Council to be better underſtood, <hi>which was not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly conformable to it, and approved of in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Anonymus</hi> looks upon theſe words,<note place="margin">Exp. p. 2.</note> and all the deſign of the Expoſition, as <hi>a Teſtimony</hi> which ſhows <hi>the Doctrine of the Roman Church</hi> (<hi>though explained ſo clearly, and decided in the Council of</hi> Trent) <hi>not yet ſo clear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An. rep. p. 11.</note> 
               <hi>but that it needs an explication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Noguier</hi> ſeems alſo to draw the ſame Conſequence,<note place="margin">Nog. p. 39.40.</note> and they have both of them looked upon the Expoſition as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication which the obſcurity of the Council ſtood in need of.</p>
            <p>But we know how the obſcurity of a Deciſion, eſpecially in matters of Faith, is not always that which makes it to be taken in a wrong ſence: it is a preoccupation of mind, the ardour of diſpute, the heat of Perſons engaged, which make them not underſtand one another, and often attribute to an adverſary what he believes the leaſt. So that when the Author of the Expoſition propoſes the Deciſions of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> to the Pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, and adds what may be uſeful to remove thoſe Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which hinder them from underſtanding them aright, they ought not to conclude from thence that the Deciſions are Ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but only that nothing is ſo well digeſted, nor ſo clear but may be underſtood amiſs, when prejudice and paſſion interpoſe.</p>
            <p>To what purpoſe then do <hi>M. Noguier</hi> and the <hi>Anonymus</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Author of the Expoſition the Bull of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV.<note place="margin">An. p. 10. Nog. p. 40.</note> The deſign of the Expoſition has nothing of thoſe Gloſſes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49682:14"/>and Commentaries which with great reaſon this Pope Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For what did thoſe Commentators and Gloſſars, eſpecially thoſe who have writ Gloſſes upon the Laws? what did they for the moſt part but fill the margents with their own imaginations, which moſt commonly ſerve only to confound the Text, and which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they give for the Text it ſelf? Let us add, that, for the conſervation of Unity, this Pope was obliged not to permit every Doctor to propoſe Deciſions upon doubts which ſucceeding time and vain ſubtilties might give birth to. Nor has any thing of this nature been done in the Expoſition. It is one thing to interpret what is obſcure and doubtful, another to propoſe what is clear, and to make uſe of it to remove falſe impreſſions. The laſt is what the Author of the Expoſition has endeavour'd preciſely. And if he have added ſome of his own Reflexions to the Deciſions of this Council, to make them more intelligible to thoſe people who would never look upon them without prejudice, it is becauſe their preocupation had need of ſuch an aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould we ſpeak any more of a thing which is clear nough? We have in few words given a certain method to enlighten the underſtandings of thoſe who are the moſt zealous to maintain this ambiguity of the Council. They need only read in this Expoſition its Decrees which are there produced, and convince themſelves by their own eyes.</p>
            <p>What is here the moſt important, is, that the Author of the Expoſition was not deceived when he promiſed what he ſhould ſay, for the better underſtanding of this Council, ſhould be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly of the ſame Spirit, and approved of in the Church. The matter is in it ſelf clear, and the following Approbations will make it apparent. It muſt not therefore be ſuppos'd henceforwards that the Sentiments explained in this work, are the qualifying or the extenuating thoughts of one man; but the Common Doctrine which we ſee is, for this reaſon, univerſally approved. It will not therefore avail <hi>M. Noguires</hi> nor the <hi>Anonymus</hi> any thing after this,<note place="margin">An. p. 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nog. 38, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> either to object to us thoſe Practices which they call general, or the particular opinion of Doctors. For without examining theſe unneceſſary things, it ſuffices in one word to ſay, thoſe Practiſes and Opinions, be they what they will, which are not found to be conformable to the intent and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions of the Council, are nothing to Religion, nor to the body
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49682:15"/>of the Catholic Church,<note place="margin">Exp. p. 2. Daille Apol. c. 6. pag. 8.</note> nor ought by conſequence, as the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reform'd do themſelves avouch, give the leaſt pretence to ſeparate from us, becauſe no one is obliged either to approve or follow them.</p>
            <p>But, ſay they, thoſe abuſes ought to be ſuppreſſed: as if one of the ways to ſuppreſs them were not to ſhew the truth in its purity without prejudice to the other means, with which Prudence and Zeal may inſpire the Biſhops. As for the remedy of Schiſm practiſed by the pretended Reformers, if it were not deteſtable in it ſelf, the miſeries which it has cauſed, and does at preſent cauſe throughout Chriſtendom, would give us a horrour of it.</p>
            <p>I will not here reproach the Pretended Reform'd with the abuſes which are amongſt them. This work of Charity does not permit ſuch like Recriminations. It ſuffices I advertiſe them that to attaque us in reality, they muſt combat, not thoſe abuſes which we Condemn as well as they, but the Doctrines which we maintain. But if in examining them more narrowly they find, they give not ſcope enough to their invectives, they ought at laſt to acknowledge we have reaſon to tell them the Faith which we profeſs is leſs worthy of blame than they believed it was.</p>
            <p>It remains at preſent, that we beg of God to grant they may read a Work without bitterneſs, which is publiſhed only to inſtruct them. The Succeſs is in his hands who can alone touch the heart. He knows the limits he has fixt to the Progreſs of Errour, and the miſeries of his afflicted Church, by the loſs of ſo great a number of her Children. But we cannot hinder our ſelves from hoping ſome great effects towards the reunion of Chriſtians, under a Pope, who exerciſes ſo piouſly and with ſo perfect a zeal, free from intereſt, the moſt holy Function in the World, and under a King who prefers before all the Conqueſts that have enlarged his Kingdom, thoſe that might gain him his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the Church.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49682:15"/>
            <head>AN EXPOSITION OF THE DOCTRINE OF THE CHURCH IN MATTERS of CONTROVERSIE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. I.</hi> The Deſign of this Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>AFter a Conteſtation, for above an Age, with thoſe of the Pretended Reform'd Religion; Matters from whence they took the ground of their Separation ought to be ſufficiently cleared, and their minds diſpoſed to a right conception of the Sentiments of the Catholic Church. So that to me nothing ſeems more proper, then to propoſe her Tenets plainly, and ſimply, and to diſtinguiſh them right from thoſe which have been falſely imputed to her. In effect, I have, upon ſeveral occaſions, taken notice, that the averſion which theſe Gentlemen have to moſt of our Sentiments, is grounded upon ſome falſe <hi>Ideas,</hi> which they have formed to themſelves, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them; or elſe upon ſome certain words, which are ſo offenſive to them, that they immediately ſtop there, and never
<pb facs="tcp:49682:16"/>come ſo far as to conſider the grounds of things. Upon which account, I thought nothing could be more beneficial, than to explicate to them what the Church has defined in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> concerning thoſe points, which keep them at fartheſt diſtant from us; without medling with that which they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to object either againſt particular Doctors, or againſt thoſe Tenets which are neither neceſſarily, nor univerſally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. For all Parties agree, and <hi>M. Daille</hi> himſelf is of that Opinion,<note place="margin">Apol. c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>it is a very unreaſonable thing to attribute the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of particular Perſons to a whole body;</hi> and he adds, that no ſeparation ought to be but upon the account of Articles authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticly eſtabliſhed, to the belief and obſervance of which all Perſons are obliged. I will not meddle then with any thing but the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> becauſe in them the Church has given her Deciſion upon theſe matters now in agitation: and what I ſhall ſay for the better underſtanding of thoſe Deciſions, ſhall be what is approved of in the Church, and ſhall manifeſtly appear conformable to the Doctrine of this Council.</p>
               <p>This Expoſition of our Doctrine will produce two good effects. The <hi>firſt,</hi> that many diſputes will wholly vaniſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will appear thev are only grounded upon ſome erroneous explications of our belief. The <hi>ſecond</hi> that thoſe diſputes, which remain, will not appear, according to the Principles of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reform'd, ſo Capital, as at the firſt they endeavoured to repreſent them; and that, according to the ſame Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, they contain nothing any ways injurious to the grounds of Faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Thoſe of the Pretended Reform'd Religion acknowledg, That the Catholic Church embraces all the Fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian Religion.</head>
               <p>ANd to begin with the fundamental and principal Articles of Faith; theſe Gentlemen of the Pretended Reform'd Religion muſt of neceſſity acknowledge they are believed and profeſſed in the Catholic Church.</p>
               <p>If they will have them to conſiſt in believing that we muſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49682:16"/>adore one only God, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and that we muſt put our truſt in God alone, through his Son, who became man, was Crucified, and roſe again for us; they know in their Conſciences that we profeſs this Doctrine: and if they add thoſe other Articles which are comprehended in the Apoſtles Creed; they do not doubt alſo but that we receive them all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, and that we have a pure and true knowledge of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Daille</hi> has writ a Treatiſe, intituled <hi>Faith founded upon the Scriptures,</hi> in which after having expoſed all the Articles of Faith held by the Pretended Reform'd Churches, he tells us, <hi>they are beyond all conteſtation;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Part</hi> 3. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>that the</hi> Roman <hi>Church profeſſes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them; that in reality they do not hold all our Opinions, but that we hold all their Articles of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Miniſter then cannot, unleſs he deſtroy his own Faith, deny but that we believe all the principal Articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>But tho' <hi>M. Daille</hi> had not granted thus much, the thing is manifeſt in it ſelf, and all the world knows, that we believe all thoſe Articles which <hi>Proteſtants</hi> call Fundamental; ſo that ſincerity it ſelf demands they ſhould without diſpute grant, that we have not really rejected any of them.</p>
               <p>The Pretended Reform'd, who ſee the advantages we may draw from this acknowledgment, are deſirous to deprive us of them, by ſaying that we deſtroy thoſe Articles, by interpoſing others contrary to them. This is what they endeavour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade by Conſequences drawn from our Doctrine; but the ſame <hi>M. Daille</hi> (whoſe authority I alledge once more, not ſo much to convince them by the Teſtimony of one of their moſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miniſters, as becauſe what he ſays is in it ſelf evident) tells them what they ought to think of ſuch kind of Conſequences, ſuppoſing ill ones might be drawn from our Doctrine. See what he writes in his Letter to <hi>M. Monglat,</hi> upon account of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie. <hi>Altho' the Opinion of the Lutherans as well as that of Rome does, according to us, infer the diſtruction of the Humanity of</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>yet this Conſequence cannot be attributed to them without Calumny, ſeeing they do formally reject it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is nothing more eſſential to the Chriſtian Religion, then the reality of the Human Nature in <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST:</hi> and yet tho' the <hi>Lutherans</hi> hold a Doctrine, from whence is inferred the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of this Capital verity, by Conſequences, which the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49682:17"/>Reform'd judge to be evident; yet they have not ſcrupled to offer to Communicate with them; becauſe their Opinion <hi>has no poyſon in it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>M. Daille</hi> tells us in his Apologie; And their National <hi>Synode,</hi> held at <hi>Charenton</hi> 1631, admits them <hi>to the Holy Table,</hi> upon this ground, <hi>that they agree in the principal and Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal points of Religion.</hi> It is then a certain Maxim eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, that they muſt not in theſe caſes look upon the Conſequences, which may be drawn from a Doctrine, but purely upon what he propoſes and acknowledges, who teaches it.</p>
               <p>So that when they infer by Conſequences, which they pretend to draw from our Doctrine, that we do not ſufficiently acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that Soveraign Glory which is due to God, nor the quality of Saviour and Mediator in <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> nor the infinite value of his Sacrifice, nor the ſuperabundant Plenitude of his Merits: we may defend our ſelves without difficulty from ſuch Conſequences, by this ſhort anſwer of <hi>M. Daille,</hi> and tell them that the Catholic Church diſavowing them, they cannot be imputed to her <hi>without Calumny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I will go yet further, and ſhow theſe Gentlemen of the Pretended Reform'd Religion, by the ſole Expoſition of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that the Catholic Church is ſo far from ruining the Fundamental Articles of Faith, either directly or indirectly; that on the contrary ſhe eſtabliſhes them after ſo ſolid and evident a manner, that no one can queſtion her right underſtanding of them without great injuſtice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Religious Worſhip is terminated in God alone.</head>
               <p>TO begin with that Adoration which is due to God alone; the Catholic Church teaches us, that it conſiſts principally, in believing he is the Creator and Lord of all things, and in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to him with all the Powers of our Soul, by Faith, Hope and Charity, as to him alone who can render us happy by the Communication of an infinite Good, which is himſelf.</p>
               <p>This interiour Adoration, which we render to God in Spirit and in Truth, has its exteriour marks; of which the principal is Sacrifice, which cannot be offered to any but to God; becauſe a Sacrifice is eſtabliſhed to make a publick acknowledgment, and a ſolemn proteſtation of Gods Soveraignity, and our abſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49682:17"/>
The ſame Church teaches us, that all Religious worſhip ought to terminate in God as its neceſſary end; and that if the honour which ſhe renders to the Bleſſed Virgin, and to the Saints may, in ſome ſence, be called Religious, it is for its neceſſary Relation to God.</p>
               <p>But before we explicate any further in what this honour conſiſts, it will not be unuſeful to take notice, how thoſe of the Pretended Reformation (obliged by the ſtrength of truth) begin to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the cuſtom of praying to Saints, and honouring their Reliques was eſtabliſhed even in the fourth age of the Church. <hi>Monſieur Daille</hi> grants thus much, in that book he publiſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Tradition of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church about the object of Religious worſhip, and accuſes St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> St. <hi>John, Chryſoſtom,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and many more of thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Lights of Antiquity who lived in that Age, and above all St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> who is called the Divine by excellence, of having altered, in this point, the Doctrine of the three fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going ages. But it will not appear very likely, that <hi>M. Daille</hi> ſhould underſtand the Sentiments of the Fathers of the firſt three Ages, better then thoſe who gathered, as I may ſay, the ſucceſſion of their Doctrine after their deaths; and this will be ſo much the leſs credible, becauſe the Fathers of the fourth Age were ſo far from perceiving that they introduced any novelty in that worſhip, that this Miniſter, on the contrary, has quoted ſeveral expreſs Texts, by which he ſhows clearly, that they pretended in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Saints, to follow the example of their Predeceſſors. But without any further examination what might be the Sentiments of the Fathers of the three firſt ages, I will content my ſelf with what <hi>M. Daille</hi> is pleaſed to grant, who allows us ſo many great men who taught the Church in the fourth age. For tho' he has taken upon him, twelve hundred years after their deaths, to give them in deriſion the name of a kind of Sect, calling them <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquariſts,</hi> that is to ſay, Relique honourers; yet I hope thoſe of his Communion will have more reſpect for theſe great men. They dare not at leaſt accuſe them of falling into Idolatry, by praying to Saints, or of deſtroying that truſt which Chriſtians ought to put in <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST:</hi> and it is to behoped henceforwards they will not reproach theſe things to us, when they conſider they cannot do it without accuſing at the ſame time theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men, whoſe ſanctity and learning they profeſs a reverence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49682:18"/>for, as well as we. But ſeeing our deſign is here to expound our belief, rather then to ſhow who were the defenders of it, we muſt continue our explication.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Invocation of Saints.</head>
               <p>THe Church in teaching us, that it is profitable to pray to Saints, teaches us to pray to them in the ſame Spirit of Charity, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame order of fraternal ſociety, which moves us to demand aſſiſtance of our brethren living upon Earth; and the Catechiſm of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> concludes from this Doctrine, that if the quality of Mediator,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cat. Rom. part</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> De Cultu &amp; Invoc. Sanct.</note> which the Scripture gives to <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> received any prejudice from the Interceſſion made to the Saints, who Reign with God, it would receive no leſs from the Interceſſion made to the faithful who live with us.</p>
               <p>This Catechiſm ſhows us clearly the extream difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt our manner of imploring God's aſſiſtance, and that of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring the aid of Saints: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith it) <hi>we pray to God, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to give us good things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Part</hi> 4. <hi>tit.</hi> Quis oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſit.</note> 
                  <hi>or to deliver us from evil; but becauſe the Saints are more acceptable to him than we are, we beg of them to undertake our cauſe, and to obtain for us thoſe things we ſtand in need of. From whence it comes to paſs, that we uſe two very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent forms of Prayer; for to God the proper manner of ſpeaking is to ſay, HAVE PITY ON <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, HEAR O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R PRAYER; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we only deſire the Saints TO PRAY FOR <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> From whence we ought to underſtand, that in what Terms ſoever thoſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which we addreſs to Saints, are couched, the intention of the Church, and of her faithful, reduces them always to this form, as the Catechiſm preſently after confirms.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But it is good to conſider the words of the Council it ſelf, which preſcribing to Biſhops how they ought to ſpeak of the Invocation of Saints,<note place="margin">Seſſ. <hi>25.</hi> Dec. de Invoc. &amp;c.</note> obliges them to teach, <hi>that the Saints who reign with</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>offer up to God their prayers for men; that it is good and profitable to invocate them after an humble manner, and to have recourſe to their prayers, aid and aſſiſtance to obtain of God his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits through our Lord</hi> JESUS CHRIST <hi>his Son, who is our ſole Saviour and Redeemer.</hi> After which the Council condemns thoſe who teach a contrary Doctrine. We ſee then, to invocate the Saints, according
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49682:18"/>to the ſenſe of this Council, is to have recourſe to their prayers for obtaining benefits from God through <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi> So that in reality we do not obtain thoſe benefits, which we receive by the interceſſion of the Saints, otherwiſe then through <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> and in his name; ſeeing theſe Saints themſelves pray in no other manner than through <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> and are not heard but in his name. This is the Faith of the Church, which the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> has clearly explicated in few words. After which we cannot imagine that any one ſhould accuſe us of forſaking <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> when we beſeech his members, who are alſo ours, his Children, who are our Brethren, and his Saints, who are our firſt fruits, to pray with us, and for us to our common Maſter, in the name of our common Mediator.</p>
               <p>The ſame Council explicates clearly and in few words, what is the intention of the Church, when ſhe offers up to God the dreadful ſacrifice to honour the memory of his Saints. This ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which we render them in Sacrificing, conſiſts in naming them in the prayers we offer up to God, as his faithful ſervants; and in rendring him thanks for the victories which they have gained, and in humbly beſeeching him that he would vouchſafe to favour us by their interceſſion. St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> has told us twelve hundred years ago,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>8.</hi> de Civ, c. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> that we ought not to think any ſacrifices were offered to the Holy Martyrs, altho' the practice of the univerſal Church in that time was to offer Sacrifice upon their holy bodies, and at their <hi>Memories;</hi> that is to ſay, before thoſe places where their pretious reliques were conſerved. This Father has moreover added,<note place="margin">Tract <hi>84.</hi> in Joh. Serm. <hi>17,</hi> in verb. Apoſt.</note> that they made a commemoration of the Martyrs at the Holy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, in the Celebration of the Sacrifice, not to pray for them as they do for other perſons who are dead; but rather, that they might pray for us. I relate the ſentiments of this Holy Biſhop, becauſe the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> makes uſe of his very words almoſt to teach the Faithful, that <hi>the Church does not offer Sacrifice to the Saint,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. <hi>22.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but to God alone, who has crowned them; that the Prieſt alſo does not addreſs himſelf to St. Peter and St. Paul, ſaying,</hi> I OFFER UP TO YOU THIS SACRIFICE; <hi>but rendring thanks to God for their victories, he demands their aſſiſtance, to the end thoſe whoſe memory we celebrate upon earth, would vouchſafe to pray for us in Heaven.</hi> It is after this manner we honour the Saints, that we may obtain the Graces of God by their Interceſſion; and the Principal of thoſe <hi>Graces</hi> we hope to obtain, is that of imitating them: to which we are excited by the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49682:19"/>conſideration of their admirable Examples, and by the honour which we render in the preſence of <hi>God</hi> to their happy memories.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who will rightly conſider the Doctrine we have propoſed, will be obliged to grant us, that as we do not rob <hi>God</hi> of any of thoſe perfections peculiar to his infinite eſſence: ſo we do not attribute to Creatures any of thoſe qualities, or operations proper to God alone: which diſtinguiſheth us ſo fully from Idolaters, we cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend why that Title ſhould be given us.</p>
               <p>And when theſe Gentlemen of the pretended Reformation object to us, that by addreſſing our Prayers to the Saints, and honouring them all the world over as preſent, we attribute to them a certain kind of Immenſity, or at leaſt the knowledg of the Secrets of hearts, which God has nevertheleſs reſerved to himſelf, as it appeares by ſo many teſtimonies of Scripture; they do not ſufficiently reflect upon our doctrine. For, <hi>in fine,</hi> without examining what grounds may be had to attribute to the Saints ſome certain degree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg as to thoſe things which are acted amongſt us, or alſo of our ſecret thoughts, it is manifeſt that to ſay a Creature may have the knowledge of theſe things, by a light communicated to him by God, is not to elevate a creature above his condition. The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Prophets juſtify this clearly, God having not diſdained to diſcover future things to them, tho they appear much more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly reſerved to his own knowledg.</p>
               <p>Moreover, never any Catholic yet thought the Saints knew our neceſſities by their own Power, no nor the deſires which move us to addreſs our ſecret Prayers to them. The Church contents herſelf to teach with all antiquity theſe Prayers to be very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to ſuch who make them, whether it be the Saints know them by the miniſtry and communication of Angels, who, according to the teſtimony of Scripture, know what paſſes amongſt us, being eſtabliſhed by Gods order, as adminiſtring Spirits, to cooperate with us in the work of our Salvation; whether it be that God himſelf makes known to them our deſires by a particular Revelation; or laſtly whether it be that he diſcovers the ſecret to them in his divine Eſſence in which all truth is compriſed. So that the Church has not decided any thing about theſe different methods, which God might be pleaſed to make uſe of for that end.</p>
               <p>But let theſe means be what they will, it is always certain the Church does not attribute to the Creature any of the divine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, as the Idolaters did; ſeeing ſhe permits us not to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49682:19"/>even in the greateſt Saints, any degree of Excellency which does not proceed from God; nor any acceptableneſs in his ſight, but by their vertues; nor any vertue, which is not a gift of his Grace; nor any knowledge of human affairs, but what is communicated to them; nor any power to aſſiſt us, but by their prayers; nor, in fine, any felicity, but by a ſubmiſſion and a perfect conformity to his divine will.</p>
               <p>It is therefore true, that by examining what are our interiour ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents concerning the Saints, it will be found we do not raiſe them above the condition of Creatures; and from thence one ought to judge of what nature that exteriour honour is, which we render them, exteriour veneration being eſtabliſhed to teſtify the interiour ſentiments of the mind.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this honour, which the Church renders to the Saints, appears principally before their Images and holy Reliques, it will be proper to explicate her belief concerning them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Images and Reliques.</head>
               <p>AS for Images,<note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. <hi>25.</hi> Dec. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voc. &amp;c.</note> the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> forbids us expreſly <hi>to believe any divinity or vertue in them, for which they ought to be reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; to demand any favour of them, or to put any truſt in them,</hi> and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains that all the honour which is given to them ſhould be referred to the Saints themſelves which are repreſented by them.</p>
               <p>All theſe words of the Council are like ſo many characters to diſtinguiſh us from Idolaters, ſeeing we are ſo far from believing with them any divinity annexed to the Images; that we do not attribute to them any other vertue but that of exciting in us the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thoſe they repreſent.</p>
               <p>Upon this it is the honour we render Images is grounded. No man, for example, can deny but that when we look upon the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> crucified, it excites in us a more lively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him, <hi>who loved us ſo as to deliver himſelf up to death for us.</hi> While this Image, being preſent before our eyes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.</note> cauſes ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious a remembrance in our ſouls, we are moved to teſtify by ſome exteriour ſigns how far our gratitude bears us; and by humbling our ſelves before the Image, we ſhow what is our ſubmiſſion to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. So that to ſpeak preciſely, and according to the Eccleſiaſtical
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49682:20"/>Stile, when we honour the Image of an Apoſtle or a Martyr, our intention is not ſo much to <hi>honour the Image,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pont. Com. de Bened. Imag. Seſſ. <hi>25.</hi> Dec. de Inv. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>as to honour the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle or the Martyr in preſence of the Image.</hi> Thus the Roman Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical tells us, and the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> expreſſes the ſame thing when it ſay, <hi>the honour we render to Images has ſuch a reference to thoſe they repreſent; that by the means of thoſe Images which we kiſs, and before which we kneel, we adore</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>and honour the Saints whoſe Types they are.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In fine, one may know with what intention the Church honours Images, by that honour which ſhe renders to the Croſs and to the Bible. All the world ſees very well, that before the Croſs ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores him who <hi>bore our Iniquities upon the wood;</hi> and that if her children bow the head before the Bible,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> if they riſe up out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, when it is carried before them, and if they kiſs it reverently, all this honour is referred to the eternal Verity which it propoſeth to us.</p>
               <p>They muſt have but little Juſtice who treat with the term of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try that Religious Sentiment, which moves us to uncover our heads, and bow them before the Image of the Croſs, in remembrance of him who was crucified for the love of us; and it would be too much blindneſs not to perceive the exceſſive difference betwixt thoſe, who put their truſt in Idols, out of an opinion that ſome divinity, or ſome vertue was, as I may ſay, tyed to them, and thoſe who declare, as we do, that they will not make uſe of Images, but to raiſe their minds towards heaven, to the end they may there honour <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> or his Saints, and in the Saints God himſelf, who is the Author of all Sanctity and Grace.</p>
               <p>After the ſame manner we ought to underſtand that honour which we pay to Reliques, after the example of the Primitive Church; and if our Adverſaries would but conſider that we look upon the bodies of Saints, as having been Victimes offered up to God either by Martyrdom or by Penance, they would not think the honour which we pay them upon this account could alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate us from that which we render to God himſelf.</p>
               <p>We may ſay in general, that if they would but conſider how the affections which we bear to any one propagates it ſelf, without being divided, to his children, to his friends, and after that, by ſeveral degrees, to the repreſentation of him, to any remains of him, and to any thing which renews in us his remembrance; If they did but conceive that honour has the like progreſſion, ſeeing honour is nothing elſe but Love mixed with reſpect and Fear; in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49682:20"/>fine, If they would but conſider, that all the exteriour worſhip of the Catholic Church has its ſource in God himſelf, and returns back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to him: they would never believe that this worſhip which he himſelf alone animates, could excite his Jealouſie. They would on the contrary ſee, that if God, as Jealous as he is of the love of men, does not look upon us as dividing our ſelves betwixt him and Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when we love our neighbour for the love of him; the ſame God, tho Jealous of the honour which his faithful pay him, cannot look upon, them as dividing that worſhip which is due to him alone, when, out of reſpect to him, they honour thoſe whom he had ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured.</p>
               <p>It is true nevertheleſs, that ſeeing the ſenſible marks of reverence are not all of them abſolutely neceſſary; the Church might without the leaſt alteration in her doctrine, extend theſe exteriour practices more or leſs according to the different exigences of times, places or occurrences, being deſirous that her Children ſhould not be ſlaviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubject to ſenſible things, but only excited, and, as it were, adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed by their means to fly to God, and to offer up to him in Spirit and in the truth that rational ſervice, which he expects from his creatures.</p>
               <p>One may ſee by this doctrine how truly I affirmed, that a great part of our Controverſies would vaniſh by the ſole underſtanding of the Terms, if theſe points were but diſcuſſed with charity; and if our adverſaries would but with moderation conſider the foregoing Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, which comprehend the expreſs doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> they would ceaſe to accuſe us of injuring the mediation of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> of Invocating the Saints, and adoring Images after a manner which is peculiar to God alone. It is true, that ſeeing, in one ſenſe, Adoration, Invocation, and the name of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator are only proper to God and <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> it is no hard matter to miſapply theſe terms, whereby to render our doctrine odious. But if they be ſtrictly kept to that ſence in which we uſe them, theſe objections and accuſations will loſe their force; and if any other leſs important difficulties remain to theſe gentlemen of the pretended Reform'd Religion, ſincerity will oblige them to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg they are ſatisfied as to the principal ſubject of their complaints.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, there is nothing ſo unjuſt as to accuſe the Church of placing all her piety in theſe devotions to the Saints, ſeeing, as we have already obſerved,<note place="margin">Seſſ. 25. Dec. de Inv. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> contents it ſelf to teach the Faithful, that this practice is <hi>good and beneficial,</hi> without ſaying
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49682:21"/>any more of it. So that the intention of the Church is only to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thoſe, who reject this practice, either out of diſreſpect or Error. She is obliged to condemn them, becauſe She is obliged not to ſuffer any practice which is beneficial to ſalvation to be deſpiſed, nor a doctrine authoriſed by antiquity to be condemned by novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE doctrine of Juſtification will ſhew yet more clearly how many difficulties may be ended by a plain expoſition of our ſentiments.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who are never ſo little verſed in the hiſtory of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reformation, are not ignorant that the firſt Authors pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed this Article to all the world as the principal of all the reſt, and as the moſt eſſential cauſe of their ſeperation; So this is the moſt neceſſary to be well underſtood.</p>
               <p>We believe in the firſt place that <hi>Our ſins are freely forgiven us by the divine mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi>'s <hi>ſake.</hi> Theſe are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs terms of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which adds, that <hi>we are ſaid to be juſtified</hi> gratis,<note place="margin">Ibid. c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>becauſe none of thoſe acts which precede Juſtification, whether they be Faith or good works, can merit this Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing the Scripture explicates the remiſſion of ſins, by ſometimes telling us that God covers them, and ſometimes that he takes them away,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5, 6, 7.</note> and blots them out by the Grace of his Holy Spirit which makes us new creatures, we believe that, to form a perfect Idea of the Juſtification of a ſinner, we muſt joyn together both theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. For which reaſon we believe our ſins not only to be covered, but alſo entirely waſhed away by the Blood of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> and by the grace of regeneration; which is ſo far from obſcuring or leſſening that Idea which we ought to have of the merit of this Blood, on the contrary it heightens and augments it.</p>
               <p>So that the Juſtice of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is not only imputed, but actually communicated to the faithful, by the operation of the Holy Spirit; in ſo much that they are not only reputed, but rendred juſt by his grace.</p>
               <p>If that Righteouſneſs which is in us were only ſuch in the eyes of men, it would not be the work of the holy Ghoſt: It is then a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49682:21"/>righteouſneſs and that before God, ſeeing it is God himſelf who produces it in us, by pouring forth his charity in our hearts.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs it is too true, that <hi>the fleſh rebels againſt the Spirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Spirit againſt the fleſh,</hi> and that <hi>we all offend in many things.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2.</note> So that, tho our Juſtice be truly ſuch, by the infuſion of his Charity, yet it is not perfect Juſtice; becauſe of the combat of Concupiſcence: In ſo much that the continual ſighings of a ſoul, penitent for her offences, is the moſt neceſſary duty of a Chriſtian righteouſneſs, which obliges us to confeſs humbly with St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that our Juſtice in this life conſiſts rather in the remiſſion of ſin, than in the perfection of Vertues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> Merits of Good Works.</head>
               <p>AS to the merit of Good works,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> the Catholic Church teacheth us, that <hi>eternal life ought to be propoſed to the children of God, both as a Grace, which is mercifully promiſed to them by the mediation of our Lord</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>and as a recompence which is faithfully ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to their good works, and merits, in vertue of this promiſe.</hi> Theſe are the proper terms of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> But leaſt human pride ſhould flatter it ſelf with an opinion of a preſumptuous merit, the ſame Council teacheth us, that all the price and value of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians works proceeds from the ſanctifying grace which is given us <hi>gratis</hi> in the name of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and that it is an effect of the continual influence of this divine Head upon its Members.</p>
               <p>Really the Precepts, Exhortations, Promiſes, Threatnings and Reproaches of the Goſpel ſhow clearly enough, we muſt work out our ſalvation by the cooperation of our wills together with the grace of God aſſiſting us: But it is one of our firſt Principles, that the free-will can act nothing conducing to eternal happineſs, but as it is moved and elevated by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>So that the Church knowing it is this divine Spirit which works in us by his Graces all the good we do; ſhe is obliged to believe the good works of the Faithful very acceptable to God, and of great conſideration before him: and it is juſt ſhe ſhould make uſe of the word <hi>Merit</hi> with all Chriſtian antiquity, whereby ſhe may principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denote the value, the price and the dignity of thoſe works which we perform through grace. But ſeeing all their Sanctity comes from God, who produces them in us, the ſame Church has in the Council
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49682:22"/>of <hi>Trent</hi> received theſe words of St. <hi>Augustin,</hi> as a doctrine of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Faith, that <hi>God crowns his own gifts in crowning the merits of his Servants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We beg of thoſe who love Truth and Peace, that they would be pleaſed here to read a little more at length the words of this Council, to the end they may once for all diſabuſe themſelves of thoſe falſe inpreſſions which has been given them concerning our doctrine. <hi>Although we ſee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> ſay the Fathers in this Council, <hi>that holy writ eſteems Good works ſo much; That</hi> JESUS CHRIST <hi>himſelf promiſes that a glaſs of cold water given to the poor ſhall not want its reward; and that the Apoſtle teſtifies how a moment of light pain endured in this world ſhall produce an eternal weight of Glory: nevertheleſs God forbid a Chriſtian ſhould glory in himſelf, and not in our Lord, whoſe bounty is ſo great to all men, that he will have thoſe gifts which he beſtowes upon them to be their merits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This doctrine is diſperſed throughout the whole Council, which teacheth us in another Seſſion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> that <hi>we, who can do nothing of our ſelves, can do all things with him who ſtrengthens us, in ſuch ſort that man has nothing of which he may glory, nor for which he may confide in himſelf; but all his confidence, and all his glory is in</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>in whom we live, in whom we merit, in whom we ſatisfy, bringing forth fruits worthy of repentance, which draw their vertue from him, and by him are offered to his Father, and accepted of by his Father through him.</hi> Wherefore we ask all things, we hope all things, we render thanks for all things, through our Lord <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi> We confeſs aloud we are not acceptable to God but in and by him, and we cannot comprehend why any other thought ſhould be attributed to us. We ſo place all the hopes of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in him, that we dayly make uſe of theſe words to God in the Sacrifice: <hi>Vouchſafe O God to grant to us ſinners, thy ſervants, who hope in the multitude of thy mercies, ſome part and ſociety with the Bleſſed Apoſtles and Martyers — into whoſe number we beſeech thee to be pleaſed to receive us, not looking upon our merits, but gratiouſly pardoning us in the name of</hi> JESUS CHRIST <hi>our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Will the Church never be able to perſwade her Children, now become her adverſaries, neither by the Expoſition of her Faith, nor by the Deciſions of her Councils, nor by the Prayers in her Sacrifice, that her belief is, that ſhe can have no life but in <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> and that ſhe has no hope but in him? This hope is ſo firm, it makes the Children of God who walk faithfully in his wayes, to find <hi>a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49682:22"/>peace which ſurpaſſeth all underſtanding,</hi> as the Apoſtle tells us.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7.</note> But tho this hope be ſtronger than the promiſes and menaces of the world, and ſufficient to calm the troubles of our Conciences; yet it does not wholy extinguiſh Fear: for tho we be aſſured God will never abandon us of his own accord, yet we are never certain we ſhall not loſe him by our own fault, in rejecting his inſpirations. He has been pleaſed by this ſaving fear to mitigate that confidence which he has infuſed into his children, becauſe, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> tells us, ſuch is our infirmity in this place of Temptations and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that an abſolute ſecurity would produce tepidity and pride in us, whereas this fear, which, according to the Apoſtles command, <hi>makes us work out our ſalvation with trembling,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12.</note> renders us more vigilant, and makes us rely with a more humble dependance upon him, <hi>who works in us by his Grace both to will, and to do, according to his good pleaſure,</hi> as the ſame St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſes it.</p>
               <p>Thus you have ſeen what is moſt neceſſary in the Doctrine of Juſtification;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> 13.</note> and our Adverſaries would be very unreaſonable, if they ſhould not confeſs that this Doctrine ſuffices to teach Chriſtians they ought to refer all the glory of their Salvation to God through <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Miniſters after this ſhould go about to move queſtions about ſubtilties it is good to advertiſe them, that it becomes them not now to be ſo ſcrupulous in our behalfs, after having granted what they have done to the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and their own brethren concerning Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination and Grace. This their conduct towards them, ought to have taught them in this matter to reduce themſelves to what is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary for the eſtabliſhment of the foundations of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian piety.</p>
               <p>But if they could but once reſolve to prefix theſe limits to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they would be preſently ſatisfied, and they would ceaſe to accuſe us of annulling the Grace of God, by attributing all to our good works; ſeeing we have ſhown them, in ſuch clear terms of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> theſe 3 points, ſo deciſive as to this matter: <hi>That our ſins are pardoned us out of pure mercy, for the ſake of</hi> JESUS CHRIST; <hi>That we are indebted for that Juſtice which is in us by the holy Ghoſt to a liberality</hi> gratis <hi>beſtowed upon us; and that all the good works we do are but ſo many gifts of his Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed we muſt acknowledge, that the learned of their Party do not contend ſo much of late about this Subject, as they did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and there are but few who do not now confeſs, there ought
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49682:23"/>not to have been a breach upon this point. But if this important difficulty about Juſtification, upon which their firſt Authors laid all their ſtreſs, be not looked upon now as eſſential by the wiſeſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons amongſt them, we leave them to think what they ought to Judge of their ſeparation, and what hopes there would be of an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if they would but overcome their prejudice, and quit the Spirit of contention.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> Satisfactions, Purgatory, and Indulgences.</head>
               <p>VVE muſt farther explicate after what manner we believe we can make ſatisfaction to God through his grace, to the end we may not leave any doubt upon this matter uncleared.</p>
               <p>Catholics unanimouſly teach, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> God and Man, was ſolely capable through the infinite dignity of his Perſon, to offer up to God a ſufficient ſatisfaction for our Sins. But having ſatisfied ſuperabundantly, he could apply this infinite ſatisfaction after two manners: either by an entire remiſſion, without reſerving any puniſhment: or elſe by changing a greater puniſhment into a leſs, that is, an eternal pain into a temporal. This firſt manner being more compleat and more comformable to his goodneſs, he makes uſe of it immediately in Baptiſm: but we believe that he makes uſe of the ſecond in the pardon he grants to thoſe who fall after Baptiſm, being carried in ſome manner to it by the ingratitude of thoſe who have abuſed his firſt gifts; ſo as they are to ſuffer ſome temporal pain tho the eternal be remitted.</p>
               <p>It muſt not be hence concluded that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> has not fully ſatisfied for us, but on the contrary, that having obtained an obſolute dominion over us, by the infinite price which he has given for our ſalvation, he grants us pardon, upon what condition, what law, or with what reſtriction it pleaſes him.</p>
               <p>We ſhould be injurious and ungrateful to our Saviour, ſhould we dare to deny the infinite value of his merits, under pretence that when he pardons us the ſin of <hi>Adam,</hi> he does not at the ſame time free us from all the conſequences of it, but leaves us ſtill ſubject to death, and ſo many other corporal and ſpiritual infirmities, which this ſin brought upon us. If ſuffices that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> has once paid the price by which we ſhall be one day entirely freed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49682:23"/>from the evils which overwhelme us; it is our parts to embrace with humility and thankſgiving every part of his benefits, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering by what progreſs it pleaſes him to procure our deliverance, according to that order which his wiſdom has eſtabliſhed for our good, and for a more clear manifeſtation of his bounty and Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Upon the like account we ought not to think it ſtrange, that he who has ſhown us ſo great mercy in Baptiſm, ſhould be more ſevere towards us, after our having violated our holy promiſes. It is juſt, yes and beneficial to our ſalvation, that God in remitting our ſin, together with the eternal pain which we deſerved for it, ſhould exact of us ſome temporal pain to retain us in our duties; leſt if we ſhould be too ſpeedily freed from the Bonds of Juſtice, we ſhould abandon our ſelves to a temerarious Confidence, abuſing the facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Pardon.</p>
               <p>It is then to ſatisfy this Obligation, we are ſubjected to ſome pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful works which we muſt accompliſh in the Spirit of Humility and Penance; and it was the neceſſity of theſe ſatisfactory works which obliged the primitive Church to impoſe upon Penitents thoſe pains called Canonical.</p>
               <p>When therefore ſhe impoſes upon Sinners painful and laborious works, and they undergo them with humility, this is called Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; and when, regarding the fervour of the Penitents, or ſome other good works which ſhe has preſcribed them, ſhe pardons ſome part of that pain which is due to them, this is called Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> propoſes nothing elſe to be believed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Indulgences,<note place="margin">Contin. ſeſt. 25. Dec. d. Indulg.</note> but that <hi>the powe to grant them has been given to the Church by</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>and that the uſe of them is beneficial to ſalvation;</hi> to which this Council adds, <hi>That this power ought to be retained, yet nevertheleſs uſed with moderation, leſt Eccleſiaſtical di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline ſhould be weakned by an over great facility:</hi> which ſhows the manner of granting Indulgences to regard diſcipline.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who depart this life in Grace and Charity, but neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs indebted to the divine Juſtice ſome pains which it reſerved, are to ſuffer them in the other life. This is what obliged all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians to offer up Prayers, Alms deeds and Sacrifices, for the faithful who departed in peace and communion of the Church,<note place="margin">Seſſ. 25. de Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</note> with a certain faith that they may be aſſiſted by theſe means. This is what the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> propoſes to us to believe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49682:24"/>touching the Souls detained in Purgatory, without determining in what their pains conſiſt, or many other ſuch like things, concerning which this Holy Council demands great moderation, blaming thoſe who divulge what is uncertain or ſuſpected.</p>
               <p>Such is the innocent and holy Doctrine of the Catholic Church touching Satisfactions, which has been imputed to her as ſo great a crime. If after this Explication, thoſe of the pretended Reform'd Religion accuſe us of injuring the ſatisfactions of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> they muſt have forgotten what we told them, that our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our payed the full price of our Redemption; that nothing is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in this price, becauſe it is infinite and how theſe remaining pains, of which we have ſpoken, come not from any defect in the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but from a certain order which he has eſtabliſhed to retain us in a ſaving diſcipline by juſt apprehenſions.</p>
               <p>But if they alſo tell us, we believe we can of our own ſelves ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy for ſome part of the pain due to our ſins, we can with confidence aſſure them, the contrary appears by the maxims we have eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. Which maxims make it clearly appear, that our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is no other but a work of Mercy and Grace; that what we do by the Grace of God is no leſs his work, then what he dos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone by his abſolute power; and laſtly, that what we give to him, appertains no leſs to him, that what he gives to us. To which we muſt add, that what we call Satisfaction, following the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the primitive Church, is after all nothing but the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the infinite ſatisfaction of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This very conſideration ought to appeaſe thoſe who are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded when we tell them, that God is ſo well pleaſed with fraternal charity and the communion of Saints, that he frequently alſo accepts of thoſe Satisfactions which we offer up one for another. It ſeems theſe men do not conceive how much all we are belongs to God, nor how all the favours, which his Goodneſs makes him have for the faithful, the members of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> are neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to this divine head. But certainly thoſe who have read and conſidered how God himſelf inſpires his ſervants with a deſire to afflict themſelves with faſting, hair-cloth and aſhes, not only for their own ſins, but alſo for the ſins of all the people, will not be aſtoniſhed if we ſay, that being touched with the delight he has to gratify his friends, he mercifully accepts of the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſacrifice of their voluntary mortifications, in abatement of thoſe chaſtiſements which he prepared for his people: which ſhows that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49682:24"/>being ſatisfied by theſe, he renders himſelf more mild towards the others, by this means honouring his Son <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> in the communion of his members, and in the holy ſociety of his myſtical body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>The Sacraments.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Order of Doctrine requires that we now ſpeak of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by which the merits of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> are applyed to us. Seeing the diſputes we have concerning them, if we except the Euchariſt, are not ſo hot as the others, we will in the firſt place clear in ſhort the cheifeſt difficuties which are raiſed concerning the other, and reſerve the Euchariſt, which is the moſt important of all the reſt, till the laſt.</p>
               <p>The Sacraments of the new Covenant are not ſacred ſigns only, which repreſent Grace, nor ſeals which confirm it to us; but the Inſtruments of the Holy Ghoſt, which ſerve to apply it to us, and which confer it upon us by vertue of the words which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, and the exteriour action which is performed, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that we put not not any Impediment by our not being rightly diſpoſed.</p>
               <p>Whilſt God annexes ſo great Grace to exteriour ſigns, which have not of their own nature any proportion with ſo admirable an effect, he ſhows us clearly, that beſides all we can do interiourly of our ſolves by our good diſpoſitions, there muſt neceſſarily intervene, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can be juſtified, a ſpecial operation of the Holy Ghoſt, and a peculiar application of the merit of our Saviour, which is exhibited to us by the Sacraments. So that this Doctrine cannot be rejected without injuring the merits of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> and the operation of his divine power in our regeneration.</p>
               <p>We acknowledg ſeven ſacred ſigns or Ceremonies eſtabliſhed by <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> as the ordinary means for the Sanctification and perfection of the new man. Their divine inſtitution appears in the holy Scripture, either by the expreſs words of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> who eſtabliſhed them, or by the Grace which, according to the ſame Scripture, is annexed to them, and neceſſarily ſhows a divine inſtitution.</p>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49682:25"/>
                  <head>Baptiſm.</head>
                  <p>Seeing little Children cannot ſupply the want of Baptiſm by acts of Faith, Hope and Charity, nor by the vow to receive this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; we believe that, if they do not really receive it, they do not in any manner partake of the Grace of redemption; and therefore dying in <hi>Adam,</hi> they have not any part in <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is good to obſerve here, that the <hi>Lutherans</hi> believe with the Catholic Church the abſolute neceſſity of Baptiſm, and are aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with her that ſuch a truth ſhould be denied, which never any one before <hi>Calvin</hi> durſt openly call in queſtion, it was ſo firmly rooted in the minds of all the faithful.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs, the Pretended Reform'd are not apprehenſive vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily to let their Children dye like the Children of Infidels, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bearing any mark of Chriſtianity, and without receiving any grace, if their deaths ſhould chance to prevent the day of their aſſembly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Confirmation.</head>
                  <p>The Impoſition of hands practiſed by the Holy Apoſtles, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Faithful againſt Perſecutions, having its principal effect in the interiour deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 8.15.17.</note> and the infuſion of his gifts, it ought not to have been rejected by our adverſaries, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that the Holy Ghoſt deſcends now no more viſibly upon us. Thus all Chriſtian Churches ſince the Apoſtles times have religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly retained it, making uſe alſo of Holy Chriſm, to ſhew the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this Sacrament by a more expreſs repreſentation of the interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our unction of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Penance, and Sacramental Confeſſion.</head>
                  <p>We believe that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> has been pleaſed, thoſe, who have ſubmitted themſelves to the Authority of the Church by Baptiſm, and who have ſince violated the laws of the Goſpel, ſhould come and ſubmit themſelves to the Judgment of the ſame Church in the Tribunal of Penance,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 18.18. <hi>John</hi> 20.23.</note> where ſhe exerciſes the power which is given her of remitting and retaining ſins.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49682:25"/>
The terms of that commiſſion which is given to the Miniſters of the Church to abſolve from ſin, are ſo general, they cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out temerity be reſtrained to publick ſins; and ſeeing when they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that abſolution in the name of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> they only follow the expreſs terms of this Commiſſion, the ſentence is looked upon as rendred by <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> himſelf, by whom they are eſtabliſhed Judges. It is this inviſible High Prieſt who interiourly abſolves the Penitent, whilſt the Prieſt exteriourly exerciſes the function.</p>
                  <p>This Penitential Court of Judicature being ſo neceſſary a curb to liberty; a ſource ſo fruitful of wiſe admonitions; ſo ſenſible a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation for ſouls afflicted for their Sins, when their abſolution is not only declared in general terms, as it is practiſed by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, but when they are in reality abſolved by the authority of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> after a particular examination, and knowledg of the Caſe: we cannot believe that our adverſaries can look upon ſo many benefits without regretting their loſs, and without being ſomewhat aſhamed of a Reformation which has caſt off ſo ſaving and ſo holy a practiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction.</head>
                  <p>The Holy Ghoſt having, according to the teſtimony of St. <hi>James,</hi> annexed an expreſs promiſe of remiſſion of ſins,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jac.</hi> 14.55.</note> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the ſick, to Extream Unction, nothing is wanting to make this ſacred ceremony a true Sacrament. It is only to be remaked, that according to the Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. <hi>c</hi> 2. de Sac. Extr. unc.</note> the ſick are more relieved in reſpect of the ſoul than of the body; and that as the ſpiritual profit is always the principal object of the new law, ſo it is that alſo which we ought abſolutely to expect from this holy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, if we be rightly diſpoſed for it; whereas the eaſe in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is only granted with a reſpect to our eternal ſalvation, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſecret diſpoſitions of the divine Providence, and the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent degrees of preparation and faith which is found in the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Marriage.</head>
                  <p>When we conſider that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> has given a new form to Marriage,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 19.5.</note> reducing this holy ſociety to two perſons immutably and indiſſolubly united; and when we ſee this inſeparable union,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.32.</note> the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49682:26"/>ſign of his eternal union with his Church: we ſhall not have my: dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to comprehend that the mariage of the Faithful is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied by the Holy Ghoſt, and by Grace; and we ſhall praiſe the divine bounty for having been thus pleaſed to conſecrate the origin of our birth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Orders.</head>
                  <p>The Impoſition of Hands, which the Adminiſtrators of ſacred things receive,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> being accompained with ſo apparent a vertue of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo full an infuſion of his Grace, it ought to be placed amongſt the number of the Sacraments. And indeed we muſt acknowledg our adverſaries do not abſolutely exclude the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of Miniſters,<note place="margin">Conf. de Foy, Art. 35.</note> but that they only exclude it from the number of the Sacraments which are <hi>common to the whole Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. X.</hi> Doctrine of the Church touching the real preſence of the Body and Blood of <hi>JESUS CHRIST</hi> in the Euchariſt, and the manner how the Church underſtand theſe words, <hi>This is my Body.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE are come, you ſee, at the laſt to the Queſtion of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, where it will be neceſſary that we explicate our Doctrine more fully, however without exceeding too much the bounds we have preſcribed our ſelves.</p>
               <p>The real preſence of the Body and Blood of our Saviour is ſolid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed by the words of the Inſtitution, which we underſtand literally; and there is no more reaſon to ask us, why we fix our ſelves to the proper and literal ſenſe, then there is to ask a Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler why he follows the high Road. It is their parts, who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the figurative ſenſe, and who take by-paths, to give a reaſon for what they do. As for us, who find nothing in the words which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> makes uſe of for the inſtitution of this myſtery, obliging us to take them in a figurative ſenſe, we think that to be a ſufficient reaſon to determine us to the literal. But we are yet more powerfully engaged, when we come to conſider in this Myſtery the intention of the Son of God, which I will explicate after the plaineſt manner I am able, and that by Principles which I think our adverſaries themſelves cannot deny.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49682:26"/>
I ſay then, Theſe words of our Saviour <hi>Take eat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 16. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>this is my body gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for you,</hi> ſhow us, that as the antient Jews did not in Spirit only unite themſelves to the Immolation of the Victim which was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for them, but that in reality they eat the ſacrifiſed fleſh, which was to them a mark of their partaking of that oblation: So <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> becoming himſelf our Victim, would have us really eat of the fleſh of his Sacrifice, to the end the actual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of this adorable fleſh might be a perpetual teſtimony to every one of us in particular, that it was for us he took it, and for us he immolated it.</p>
               <p>God had forbidden the Jews to eat of the ſin-offering, to teach them the true expiation of their crimes was not to be accompliſhed in the Law, nor by the blood of Beaſts: all the people lay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 6.30.</note> as it were, under an interdiction by this prohibition, without being able to have any actual participation of the remiſſion of Sins. By a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary reaſon it was neceſſary the Body of our Bleſſed Saviour, the true Hoſt immolated for ſin, ſhould be eaten by the Faithful, to ſhow them by this eating that the remiſſion of ſin was accompliſhed in the new Teſtament.</p>
               <p>God alſo forbid the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to eat Blood;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.11.</note> and one of the reaſons for this Prohibition was, becauſe the <hi>Blood was given us for the Expiation of our Souls.</hi> But on the contrary, our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour gives us his Blood to drink,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 26.28.</note> becauſe <hi>it is ſhed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that the eating of the Body and Blood of the Son of God is as real at the Holy Table, as the Grace, the expiation of Sins, and the participation of the Sacrifice of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is actual and real in the new Covenant.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, ſeeing he deſired to exerciſe our Faith in this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and at the ſame time, to free us from the horror of eating fleſh, and drinking Blood in their proper Species, it was convenient he ſhould give us them cloathed under another Species. But if theſe Conſiderations have obliged him to make us partake of the fleſh of our Victim after another manner than the <hi>Jews,</hi> he was not for that obliged to deprive us in the leaſt of the reality of his Subſtance.</p>
               <p>It appears then, to accompliſh the antient Figures, and to put us in actual Poſſeſſion of the Victim offered for our Sins, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> had intention to give us really his Body and Blood. Which is ſo evident, that our Adverſaries themſelves would have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49682:27"/>us to believe they are in this of the ſame opinion with us, perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally repeating how they deny not the actual Preſence, nor the real Participation of the Body and Blood in the Euchariſt. This we will examine hereafter, where we think it neceſſary to repreſent their Sentiments, after we have finiſhed the Explication of thoſe of the Church. But in the mean time we will conclude, that if the plainneſs of our Saviours words has forced them to acknowledg, his expreſs Intention was to give us in reality his Fleſh, when he ſaid, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> they ought not to be aſtoniſhed, if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſent to underſtand theſe words only in Figure.</p>
               <p>In reality, the Son of God, who was ſo careful to explicate to his Apoſtles what he taught them under Parables and Figures, having ſaid nothing here to explicate himſelf, it appears he left theſe words in their natural Signification. I know theſe Gentlemen pretend the Nature of the thing explains it ſelf ſufficiently, becauſe we ſee very well, ſay they, what he preſents us is nothing but Bread and Wine; but this reaſon vaniſhes, when we conſider, he who ſpeaks has an Authority which over-rules the Senſes, and a Power which has Dominion over univerſal Nature.</p>
               <p>The Son of God has no more difficulty to render his Body preſent in the Euchariſt, by ſaying, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> than to Cure a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of her Infirmity,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 13.12.</note> by ſaying, <hi>Woman thou art freed from thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity;</hi> or to preſerve the Life of a young Man, by ſaying to his Father,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 4.50.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy Son liveth;</hi> or to forgive the Sins of the Man ſick of the Palſy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.2.</note> by ſaying to him, <hi>Thy Sins are forgiven thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that, not troubling our ſelves how he will execute what he has ſaid, we reſt preciſely upon his words. He who does what he will, by ſpeaking does what he pleaſes; and it was more eaſy for the Son of God to force the Laws of Nature to verify his word, than it is for us to accommodate our Underſtandings to theſe kind of violent Interpretations, which break the Laws of common Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe Laws of Diſcourſe teach us, that a ſign which repreſents a thing naturally, receives often the name of the thing repreſented, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it were its nature to bring the Idea of the thing into the Mind. The ſame alſo happens, tho with ſome reſtriction, to inſtituted Signs, when they are received, and Perſons accuſtomed to them. But that, in eſtabliſhing a Sign, which has no relation to the thing, as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a Morſel of Bread to ſignify the Body of a Man, the name of the thing ſignified ſhould be given to it with out any Explication, and before any agreement, as <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> has done in his laſt Supper, is a thing unheard of, and of which we find no exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49682:27"/>in holy Writ, not to ſay in any Language. Neither do the Gentlemen of the Pretended Reform'd Religion ſo fix themſelves to the figurative Senſe, which they would give to theſe words of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> but that they do at the ſame time acknowledge, he had intention in pronouncing them to give us in reality his Body and Blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI. <hi>Explication of theſe Words,</hi> Do this in remembrance of me.</head>
               <p>AFter having propoſed the Sentiments of the Church, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> we muſt explicate what ſhe thinks of thoſe others, which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> added, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me.</hi> It is manifeſt, the intention of the Son of God is to oblige us by theſe words,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.19.</note> to remember the Death which he has endured for our Salvation,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.24.</note> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> concludes from theſe ſame words, that we <hi>declare the Death of our Saviour</hi> in this Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But they muſt not perſwade themſelves,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</note> that remembrance of our Saviours Death, excludes the real Preſence of his Body: on the contrary, if they conſider what we have lately explicated, they will clearly underſtand this Commemoration to be grounded upon the real Preſence. For as the <hi>Jews</hi> in eating of the Peace-Offerings remembred they had been immolated for them; in the ſame manner in eating of the fleſh of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> our Victim, we ought to remember he died for us. This very fleſh then, eaten by the Faithful, not only renews in us the memory of his immolation, but confirms alſo to us the reality of it. And we are ſo far from having reaſon to ſay, that this ſolemn Commemoration, which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> ordains us to make, excludes the Preſence of his Body, that, on the contrary, we ſee this tender remembrance which he would have us to make at the Holy Table of him, as immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated for us, is grounded upon this; that this very fleſh ought to be there taken really, ſeeing in effect it is not poſſible for us to forget it was for us he gave his Body in Sacrifice, when we ſee he daily gives us the ſame Victime to eat.</p>
               <p>Muſt Chriſtians under pretence of celebrating in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the memory of the Paſſion of our Saviour. deprive this Pious Commemoration of what it has moſt efficacious and tender in it? Ought they not to conſider, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> does not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49682:28"/>them only to remember him, but to remember him in eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Fleſh and Blood? Conſider the Connexion, and the force of his words. He does not ſay ſimply, as thoſe of the Pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation ſeem to underſtand him, That the Bread and Wine of the Euchariſt ſhould be to us a <hi>Memorial</hi> of his Body and Blood; but he advertiſes us, that in doing what he has preſcribed, that is, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his Body and Blood, we ſhould remember him. What is there in reality more powerful to make us remember him? And if Children do ſo tenderly remember their Parents, and their Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties towards them, when they approach the Tombs where their Bodies are interred; how ought our Remembrance, and our Love to be excited, when we poſſeſs under theſe ſacred Vails, under this myſtical Sepulchre, this living and Life-giving Fleſh, and this Blood yet flowing with his Love, and full of Spirit and Grace? But if our Adverſaries continue to tell us, That he who commands us to remember him, does not give us his proper Subſtance, we muſt in fine, deſire them to agree amongſt themſelves. They profeſs not to deny the real Communication of the proper ſubſtance of the Son of God in the Euchariſt. If their words are ſerious, if their Doctrine be not an illuſion, they muſt neceſſarily ſay with us, the remembrance does not exclude all kinds of Preſence, but only that which ſtrikes the Senſes. Their Anſwer ſhall be ours, ſeeing that tho we affirm <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> to be preſent, yet we acknowledg at the ſame time, that he is not preſent after a ſenſible manner.</p>
               <p>And if it ſhould be demanded, how it comes to paſs, that belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as we do, the Senſes to have nothing to do in this Myſtery, we ſhould not believe it ſufficient that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> ſhould be preſent by Faith: It is eaſie to anſwer, and to clear this Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Objection. It is one thing to ſay, the Son of God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to us by Faith, and another thing to ſay, we know by Faith that he is preſent. The firſt manner of ſpeaking, imports only a moral preſence; but the ſecond ſignifies to us a very real one, becauſe our Faith is moſt real; and this real Preſence known by Faith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Habac.</hi> 2.4.</note> is ſufficient to work all the forementioned Effects in the <hi>Juſt Man, who lives by Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49682:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XII.</hi> Expoſition of the <hi>Calvaniſts</hi> Doctrine concerning the real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</head>
               <p>BUT to remove all the Equivocations which <hi>Calviniſts</hi> make uſe of in this matter, and ſhow at the ſame time, how near they have approached to us, it will be convenient to add here, the expoſition of their Sentiments, tho I only undertook to explicate the Doctrine of the Church.</p>
               <p>Their Doctrine has two parts; the one ſpeaks of nothing but the Figure, and the other of nothing but the Reality of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> We ſhall ſee each of theſe parts in order.</p>
               <p>They tell us firſt, This great Miracle of the real Preſence, which we admit, is uſeleſs; that it is enough for our Salvation, <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> died for us; that his Sacrifice is ſufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to us by Faith; and that this application is ſufficiently cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified to us by the Word of God. They add, That if this Word muſt be clothed with ſenſible Signs, it is enough to give ſimple Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols, ſuch as the Water of Baptiſm, without any neceſſity of fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Body and Blood of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> from Heaven.</p>
               <p>There ſeems to be nothing more eaſie than this manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicating the Sacrament of the Lords Supper. Nevertheleſs, our Adverſaries themſelves do not think it ought to ſuffice them. They know ſuch kind of Imaginations made the <hi>Socinians</hi> deny the great Miracle of the Incarnation. God might have ſaved us, ſay theſe Hereticks, without ſo much difficulty; he had nothing to do, but to pardon out faults, and might have inſtructed us ſufficiently, as well in Faith, as in Manners, by the Preaching and Examples of a Man full of the Holy-Ghoſt, without any need of making him a God. But the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> as well as we, ſee the weakneſs of this Argument, which appears firſt from its not appertaining to us to deny or affirm Myſteries, according as they appear to us uſeful or unprofitable to our Salvation. God alone knows the Secret; and it is our buſineſs to render them uſeful and ſaving to us, in belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them as he propoſes them, and in receiving his Graces after the manner he beſtows them upon us. Secondly, not to enter into the queſtion, whether it was poſſible for God to ſave us by any other means than the Incarnation, and Death of his Son, and not to meddle
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49682:29"/>with that unneceſſary diſpute, which the Pretended Reform'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion treats of ſo at length in the Schools, it ſuffices, we have learnt from the Scriptures, that the Son of God has been pleaſed to teſtifie his Love to us by incomprehenſible Effects. This Love has been the Cauſe of this ſo real an Union, by which he was made Man. This Love moved him to immolate the ſame Body for us, as really as he united himſelf to it. All theſe deſigns are conſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and this Love maintains it ſelf in all things with the ſame vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour. So that, when it ſhall pleaſe him to make each of his Children experience the goodneſs which he has teſtified to all in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, by giving himſelf to them in particular, he will find out a method to accompliſh his Deſires, by no leſs efficacious means, than thoſe by which he had already accompliſhed our Salvation. Upon which account we muſt not be hereafter aſtoniſhed, if he give to each of us the proper Subſtance of his Body and Blood. He does it that he may imprint this in our Hearts, that it was for us he took them, and for us he offered them up in Sacrifice. That which preceded, makes all that follows credible to us; the order of his Myſteries diſpoſe us to believe all this; and his expreſs word permits us not to doubt of it.</p>
               <p>Our Adverſaries ſaw very well, that ſimple figures and ſigns of his Body and Blood would not content Chriſtians, who are accuſtomed to the Bounties of a God, who gives himſelf to us ſo really. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will not ſuffer us to accuſe them of denying a real and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial participation of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> in their Supper. They affirm,<note place="margin">Cat. Dim. <hi>53.</hi>
                  </note> as well as we, that he makes us there Partakers <hi>of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Subſtance;</hi> they tell us, that he <hi>nouriſhes and quickens us with the ſubſtance of his Body and Blood;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conf. of Faith, <hi>art.</hi> 36.</note> and judging that it would not be enough to ſhew us, by ſome ſign, that we are partakers of his Sacrifice,<note place="margin">Cat. Dim. <hi>52.</hi>
                  </note> they ſay expreſly, that the Body of our Saviour, which is given us in the laſt Supper, aſſures us of it: words very remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, which we will examine by and by.</p>
               <p>Behold then the Body and Blood of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> preſent in our Myſteries, by the acknowledgment of the <hi>Calviniſts:</hi> for what is communicated <hi>according to its proper ſubſtance,</hi> muſt be really preſent. It is true, they explicate this Communication, by ſaying, it is in Spirit, and by Faith: but it is true alſo, they will have it real. And becauſe it is impoſſible to make it intelligible how a Body, that is communicated to us only in Spirit, and by Faith, can be communicated to us really, and in its proper ſubſtance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49682:29"/>therefore they have not been able to continue firm in the two parts of a Doctrine ſo contradictory, and they have been obliged to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg two things which cannot be true, but by ſuppoſing what the Catholic Church teacheth.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, That <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is given to us in the Euchariſt after a manner whch neither agrees with that of Baptiſm, nor the Preaching of the Goſpel, but is peculiar to this Myſtery. We ſhall ſee by and by the Conſequence of this Principle: but let us firſt ſee how it is granted us by thoſe of the Pretended Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>I will not here alledge the Authority of any particular Author, but the proper words of their Catechiſm, where it explicates what concerns the laſt Supper. It does not only tell us in expreſs terms, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is given us in the Supper, in reality, and <hi>according to his proper Subſtance;</hi> but that,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dim.</hi> 53.</note> 
                  <hi>tho he be truly commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to us, both by Baptiſm, and the Goſpel, yet nevertheleſs, it is only in part, and not fully.</hi> From whence it follows, that he is given us in the Lords Supper fully, and not in part.</p>
               <p>There is a vaſt difference betwixt receiving in part, and receiving fully. If then we receive <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> every where elſe in part, and it be only in the Lords Supper we receive him fully; it follows, by the conſent of our Adverſaries, that we muſt look out for a participation in the laſt Supper which is proper only to this Myſtery, and which does not agree with Baptiſm and Preaching; but at the ſame time it follows alſo, that this participation is not annexed to Faith, becauſe Faith being generally diſperſed through all the Actions of a Chriſtian, is found in Preaching, and in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as well as in the Lords Supper. In reality, it is remarkable, that what deſire ſoever the Pretended Reformers had to render Baptiſm and Preaching equal to the laſt Supper, becauſe <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is there truly communicated to us, they durſt never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm in their Catechiſms, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is given us, in his proper Subſtance, by Baptiſm and Preaching, as they ſay he is given in the Euchariſt. They ſaw then, they could not avoid at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to the Euchariſt a manner of poſſeſſing <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> peculiar only to this Sacrament; and that Faith, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the Actions of a Chriſtian, could not be this particular manner. But this peculiar manner of poſſeſſing <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> in the laſt Supper ought alſo to be real, ſeeing it gives to the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful the proper ſubſtance of the Body and Blood of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49682:30"/>CHRIST.</hi> So that we muſt conclude, from what they grant us, there is in the Euchariſt a real manner of receiving the Body and Blood of our Saviour, which is not performed by Faith; and this is what the Catholic Church teaches.</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing granted by the Pretended Reformers, is taken out of that Article which immediately follows that which I have already cited out of their Catechiſm;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dim.</hi> 52.</note> which is, <hi>That the Body of our Lord</hi> JESUS, <hi>for as much as it was once offered up in Sacrifice to reconcile us to God, is now given to aſſure us, we have a part in that Reconciliation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there be any Senſe in theſe Words, if they be not an uſeleſs found, and a vain amuſement, we ought to underſtand by them, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> does not give us a Symbol only, but his proper Body, to aſſure us, we partake of his Sacrifice, and of the Reconciliation of Mankind. But if the reception of the Body of our Lord, aſſures us of our participation of the Fruits of his Death; this participation of the Fruits muſt neceſſarily be diſtinguiſhed from the reception of the Body, ſeeing one is the pledg of the other. From whence, to proceed, I ſay, If our adverſaries are forced to diſtinguiſh in the laſt Supper the participation of the body of our Bleſſed Saviour, from the participation of the fruits of his Grace in his Sacrifice, they muſt alſo neceſſarily make a diſtinction between the participation of this Divine Body, and all kinds of Spiritual participation by Faith. This latter participation will never furniſh them with two diſtinct Actions, by one of which they receive the Body of our Saviour, and by the other, the benefit of this Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; no man being able to conceive what difference there is betwixt partaking by Faith of the Body of our Saviour, and partaking by Faith of the Fruit of his Death. They muſt therefore acknowledg, that beſides the Communion, by which we ſpiritually partake of the Body of our Saviour, and alſo of his Spirit, by receiving the fruit of his Death; there is alſo a Real Communion of the Body of the ſame Saviour, which is to us a certain Pledg of the others being aſſured to us, if we put no impediment to ſuch a Grace by an evil Diſpoſition. This is neceſſarily included in the Principles they admit, and they will never be able to explicate this Truth, with the leaſt ſhadow of Solidity, if they return not to the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church.</p>
               <p>Who will not here admire the force of Truth? All the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which follow from the acknowledged Principles of our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49682:30"/>are perfectly underſtood in the ſentiment of the Church. Catholicks, the meanlieſt inſtructed, without difficulty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that in the Euchariſt there is a Communion which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> which is not to be found any where elſe. It is no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty for them to underſtand his Body <hi>is given us, to aſſure us we partake of his Sacrifice and of his Death.</hi> They diſtinguiſh clearly betwixt theſe two neceſſary manners of uniting or ſelves to <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST;</hi> the one in receiving his proper fleſh, the other in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his Spirit; the firſt of which is granted us, as a certain pledge of the ſecond. But ſeeing theſe things are inexplicable in the ſentiments of our adverſaries, tho on the other hand they cannot deny them, we muſt neceſſarily conclude, that errour has thrown them into a manifeſt contradiction.</p>
               <p>I have been often aſtoniſhed they did not explicate their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine after a more plain manner. Why did they not always, without ſo many formalities, perſevere to ſay, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> having ſhed his Blood for us, repreſented to us this effuſion, by giving us two diſtinct ſigns of his Body and Blood; that he was pleaſed indeed to give to theſe ſigns the name of the thing it ſelf: that theſe ſacred ſigns were pledges to aſſure us of our partaking of the fruit of his Death, and that we were ſpiritually nouriſhed by the vertue of his Body and Blood? After ſo many endeavours to prove that ſigns often receive the names of the things ſignified, and that for this reaſon the ſign of the Body might be called the Body, all this connection of Doctrine obliges them naturally to fix there. To render theſe ſigns efficacious, it ſufficed the Grace of Redemption was annexed to them, or rather, according to their Principles, that it was in them confirmed to us. They needed not have tormented themſelves, as they have done, to make us underſtand we receive the proper Body of our Saviour, to aſſure us we partake of the Grace of his Death. They were well enough ſatisfied to have the water of Baptiſm a ſign of the Blood which waſheth us; and it never entred into their fancies to ſay, we there received the proper ſubſtance of the Blood of our Bleſſed Saviour, to aſſure us his vertue is there diffuſed upon us. If they had argued after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as to the Euchariſt, their Doctrine would have been leſs em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyled. But thoſe who invent and innovate, cannot expreſs all they have a mind to. They find certain truths, and maxims eſtabliſhed which incommode them, and force a violence upon their imaginations. The <hi>Arians</hi> would gladly have reſuſed our Bleſſed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49682:31"/>Saviour the name of God, or the only Son of God. The <hi>Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> did not admit, but with reluctance, that kind of I know not what unity of perſon in <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> which we find in their writing. The <hi>Pelagians,</hi> who denied Original ſin, would alſo willingly have denyed that Baptiſm was given to little children for the remiſſion of ſins: for by that means they would have been freed from the argument which Catholicks drew from this practice to prove that original defect. But, as I juſt now ſaid, thoſe who find ſome truths firmly eſtabliſhed, have not the boldneſs, or rather impudence to overthrow all. Let the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> ingenuouſly confeſs the truth; they would have been well pleaſed to acknowledge in the Euchariſt the Body of our Bleſſed Saviour only figuratively, and the ſole participation of his Spirit in effect, laying aſide thoſe great words of <hi>Participation of his proper ſubſtance,</hi> and the many others which import a real preſence, and ſerve only to perplex them. It would have been more to their humour, to have acknowledged, in the Lords Supper, no other communion with <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> but what is alſo common to Preaching and to Baptiſm, without tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, as they have done, that in the Lords Supper <hi>he is received in plentitude,</hi> and every where elſe only <hi>in part.</hi> But however this was their inclination, yet the very force of the terms oppoſed them, our Bleſſed Saviour having ſaid ſo preciſely of the Euchariſt, <hi>This is my body, This is my Blood;</hi> which he never did of any other thing, nor upon any other occaſion: what likelihood was there of rendring that common to all the Actions of a Chriſtian, which his expreſs word had annexed to one particular Sacrament? And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the whole order of divine providence, the connexion of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Holy Myſteries, the intention of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> in his laſt Supper, the words themſelves which he uttered, and the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which they naturally form in the minds of the Faithful, give us nothing but the Ideas of his real preſence. Therefore it was neceſſary our adverſaries ſhould find out ſome expreſſions, the ſound of which might, at leaſt, give us a confuſed Idea of this reality. When a Man fixes himſelf either entirely upon Faith, as Catholicks do; or entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon humane Reaſon, as Infidels do, it is eaſie for him to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh a connected and uniform model of Doctrine. But when a man goes about to make a compoſition of one and the other, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſays ſomething which he would not ſay, and afterwards falls into opinions, the ſole contrarieties of which ſhew the manifeſt falſity of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49682:31"/>
This is what has hapned to theſe Gentlemen of the pretended reform'd Religion; and God has ſo permitted it to facilitate their return to Catholic unity. For, whereas their proper experience ſhows them, they muſt neceſſarily expreſs themſelves as we do, to ſpeak the language of Truth; ought they not to judge it neceſſary to think as we do, to underſtand it right? If they obſerve in their own belief many expreſſions, which have no ſence but according to our tenets; is it not ſufficient to convince them, that Truth is not in its full perfection but amongſt us? And thoſe unconnected parts of Catholick Doctrine, which are ſcatered here and there in their Catechiſms, but which, as I may ſay, require to be united to the whole, ought they not to excite them to ſearch, in the Communion of the Church, a full and entire explication of the Myſtery of the Euchariſt? They would, no doubt of it, be brought to it, did not humane Reflections trouble and perplex their Faith, which has too much dependance upon Sence. But having ſhown what Fruit they ought to reap from the Expoſition of their Doctrine, let us finiſh the explication of our own.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIII.</hi> Of Tranſubſtantiation and Adoration, and in what ſence the Euchariſt is ſaid to be a Sign.</head>
               <p>IT having been convenient, as it was ſaid before, that the Senſes ſhould not perceive any thing in this Myſtery of Faith, it was neceſſary nothing ſhould be changed, in reſpect of them, in the Bread and Wine of the Euchariſt. Upon which account, being we ſee the ſame Species, and feel the ſame Effects as before in this Sacrament, we muſt not wonder, if the ſame name be given to them ſometimes, and in ſome certain Senſe. Yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Faith being attentive to his word, who performs what pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es him in Heaven, and on Earth, acknowledges here no other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but what is deſigned by the ſame word, that is to ſay, the proper Body and Blood of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> into which the Bread and Wine are changed; this is what we call Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>However, That real verity, which is interiorly contained in the Euchariſt, hinders not the exterior and ſenſible part from being
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49682:32"/>a ſign; but a ſign of ſuch a Nature, that it is ſo far from exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reality of the thing ſignified, it bears it neceſſarily along with it, ſeeing that in effect, theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd upon that matter, which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> himſelf made choice of, is to us a certain ſign that his Body is preſent, and though the Symbols appear always the ſame to our Senſes, yet our Mind judges otherwiſe of them, and not according to Senſe, becauſe a Superior Authority interpoſes. So that, whereas certain Species, and a certain ſequel of natural impreſſions on our Senſes, have been accuſtomed to deſign to us the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine, the Authority of Him, in whom we believe, cauſes theſe ſame Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to begin to ſhew us another ſubſtance. For we give ear to him who ſaid, that <hi>this, which we receive and eat, is his Body;</hi> and ſuch is the force of theſe words, they hinder us from referring thoſe exteriour appearances to the Subſtance of Bread, and induced us to refer them to the Body of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> there preſent: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the preſence of ſuch an adorable Object being rendered certain to us by this ſign, we are not afraid to pay it our adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>I will not dwell upon the point of Adoration, becauſe the moſt learned and the moſt intelligent of our Adverſaries have long ſince granted us, thoſe who are perſwaded of the real Preſence of <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> in the Euchariſt ought to pay him in it their Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
               <p>In fine, being once convinced, the all-powerful words of the Son of God operate whatever they declare, we believe that in the laſt Supper, they had their effect as ſoon as they were pronounced by him; and by a neceſſary Conſequence we acknowledg the real Preſence of his Body, before our receiving of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIV.</hi> Sacrifice of the Maſs.</head>
               <p>THeſe things being ſuppoſed, there remains no particular diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty about the Sacrifice which we acknowledg in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</p>
               <p>We have obſerved two actions in this Myſtery, which ceaſe not to be diſtinct, the one of them has a Relation to the other. The
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49682:32"/>firſt is the conſecration, by which the Bread and Wine are changed into the Body and Blood; and the ſecond is the receiving, by which we partake of them.</p>
               <p>In the Conſecration, the Body and the Blood are myſtically ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, becauſe <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> ſaid ſeparately, <hi>This is my Body, this is my Blood;</hi> which includes a lively and efficacious Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the violent Death he ſuffered.</p>
               <p>So that the Son of God is placed upon the Holy Table, in vertue of theſe words, cloathed with thoſe ſigns which repreſent his Death, this is effected by conſecration; and this Religious action, carries with it an acknowledgment of Gods Soveraignty, in as much as <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> there preſent, renews and perpetuates in ſome ſort, the remembrance of his being obedient, even to the Death of the Croſs: So that there is nothing wanting to render this a true Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>We cannot doubt but this Action, as diſtinct from that of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating, is of it ſelf acceptable to God, and makes him look upon us with a more propitious Eye, becauſe it repreſents to him that voluntary Death which his beloved Son has ſuffered for us Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or rather places before his Eyes, that very Son of his, under the ſigns of this Death, by which his Wrath had been appeaſed.</p>
               <p>All Chriſtians will confeſs the ſole Preſence of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> to be a moſt Powerful Interceſſion before God for all mankind; according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle, That <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST preſents himſelf and appears for us before the Face of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24.</note> So that we believe that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> being preſent upon the Holy Table, under this Figure of Death, intercedes for us, and repreſents continually to his Father that Death which he has ſuffered for his Church.</p>
               <p>It is in this Senſe we ſay, <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> offers up himſelf to God for us in the Euchariſt; it is after this manner we conceive this Oblation renders God more propitious to us, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we call this a Propitiatory Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>When we conſider what it is, <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> operates in this Myſtery, and that we ſee him by Faith preſent upon this Holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, together with theſe Signs of Death, we unite our ſelves to him in this Eſtate; we preſent him to God, as our only Victim, and our ſole Propitiator by his Blood, confeſſing we have nothing to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up to God but <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> and the infinite Merit of his Death. We conſecrate all our Prayers by this Holy Oblation, and in preſenting <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> to God, we learn at the ſame
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49682:33"/>time, to offer up our ſelves to the Divine Majeſty in him, and by him, as living Sacrifices.</p>
               <p>This is the Sacrifice of Chriſtians, infinitely different from what was offered up in the Old Law: a Spiritual Sacrifice becoming the New Covenant, in which the preſence of the Victim is only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by Faith; in which the Word of God is the Spiritual Sword which makes a Myſtical ſeparation betwixt the Body and the Blood; in which by conſequence the Blood is only ſhed My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically, and in which Death only intervenes by repreſentation: and yet however a moſt real Sacrifice, in as much as <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is there truly contained, and preſented to his Father, under this Figure of Death: But a Commemorative Sacrifice, which is ſo far from taking away our adheſion to the Sacrifice of the Croſs (as it is objected to us) on the contrary, it fixes us the firmer to it by all its circumſtances; ſeeing it has not only an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire relation to it, but in reality, has neither being nor ſubſiſtence but by this relation, from whence it deriveth all the Vertue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it.</p>
               <p>This is the expreſs Doctrine of the Catholic Church in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which teaches, that this Sacrifice is inſtituted only <hi>to repreſent that which was once accompliſhed upon the Croſs;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>to perpetuate the memory of it to the end of the World; and to apply to us the ſaving Vertue of it for the remiſſion of thoſe ſins which we commit every day.</hi> So that the Church is ſo far from believing, that ſomething wants to perfect the Sacrifice of the Croſs; on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, ſhe thinks it ſo perfect, and ſo fully ſufficient, as what is added, is only inſtituted to celebrate the memory, and apply its Vertue.</p>
               <p>By which the ſame Church acknowledges, that all the merit of the Redemption of Mankind depends upon the Death of the Son of God; and it ought to be underſtood, from all we have already expounded, that when we ſay to God in the Celebration of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Myſtery, <hi>We offer unto you this Holy Hoſt,</hi> we pretend not by this Oblation, to make, or preſent to God a new payment of the price of our Salvation, but to offer up to him in our behalfs, the Merits of our Bleſſed <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> there preſent, and the infinite price which he once paid for us upon the Croſs.</p>
               <p>The Gentlemen of the Pretended Reform'd Religion do not think they offend <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> by offering him to God as preſent to their Faith; and if they believed him to be really there,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49682:33"/>what repugnance could they have to offer him up as truly preſent; So that the whole diſpute ought indeed to be reduced to the real preſence alone.</p>
               <p>From hence forwards, all thoſe falſe Ideas, which theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Pretended Reform'd Religion form to themſelves of the Sacrifice which we offer, ought to be effaced. They ought freely to acknowledge Catholics pretend not to make a new propitiation to appeaſe God anew, as if he had not been ſufficiently ſatisfied by the Sacrifice of the Croſs; or to make ſome addition to the Price of our Salvation, as if it were imperfect. All theſe things have no place in our Doctrine; becauſe all that is here done, is intended by way of Interceſſion and Application, after the manner which we have now explicated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XV.</hi> The Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter this Explication, thoſe mighty Objections drawn from the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and ſo much enforced againſt us, will appear to have little reaſon in them: and it is in vain our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſtrive to prove, from the ſentiments of the Apoſtle, that we annul the Sacrifice of the Croſs. But becauſe the beſt way to prove that two Doctrines are not oppoſite to one another, is to ſhew, by explicating them, that no propoſition of the one is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to any of the propoſitions of the other; I think I am bound in this place to propoſe in ſhort the Doctrine of this Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle intends in this Epiſtle to teach us, that a ſinnner could not avoid Death, but by ſubſtituting ſome one in his place to die for him; that whilſt Men ſubſtituted only Beaſts to be killed in their places, their Sacrifices operated nothing, but a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick acknowledgment of their having deſerved Death; and that, ſeeing the Divine Juſtice could not be ſatisfied by ſo unequal an exchange, they begun again every day to ſlay new Victims; which was a certain mark of the inſufficiency of that ſubſtitution: But that, ſince <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> had vouchſafed to die for Sinners, God being ſatisfied, by a Perſon ſubſtituting of himſelf, ſo condignly ſufficient, and nothing more to exact for the price of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. From whence the Apoſtle concludes, we ought not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to offer up no more Victims after <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> but that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49682:34"/>
                  <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> himſelf ought to be but once offered up to Death for us.</p>
               <p>Let the Reader then, who is ſolicitous for his Souls Salvation, and a lover of Truth, reflect a little upon what we have ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manner how <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> offers up himſelf to God for us in the Euchariſt; I am certain, he will not find any Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on contrary to thoſe which I have here related from the Apoſtle; or which weakens his Argument; ſo that nothing can be objected to us, but his ſilence upon this point. But thoſe who would but conſider the wiſe diſtribution which God makes of his ſecrets in the ſeveral Books of Scripture, would not oblige us to receive, from the ſole Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> all our inſtructions concerning a matter which was not neceſſary to the Subject of that Epiſtle; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle intends to explicate in it, the perfection of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Croſs, and not the different manners which God has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted to apply it to us.</p>
               <p>And to remove all equivocation, if we take the word <hi>Offer</hi> in the ſence it is made uſe of in this Epiſtle, as implying the actual Death of the Victim, we will publickly confeſs, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is now no more offered up, neither in the Euchariſt, nor any where elſe. But becauſe this word has a larger ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in other places of Scripture, where it is often ſaid, We offer up to God what we preſent before him; the Church, which forms her Language, and her Doctrine not from the ſole Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> but from the whole Body of the Holy Scripture, is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to ſay, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> offers up himſelf to God whereever he appears before his Face upon our behalf, and that by conſequence, he offers up himſelf in the Euchariſt, according to the Holy Fathers expreſſions.</p>
               <p>Now to imagine this manner, by which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelf to God, ſhould injure the Sacrifice of the Croſs, is what cannot in any kind be ſuppoſed without overthrowing the the whole Scripture, and particularly this Epiſtle, which is ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently objected againſt us. For it muſt, by the ſame reaſon, be concluded, that when <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> offered up himſelf to God, <hi>In entring into the World,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5.</note> to ſubſtitute himſelf in place of thoſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctims <hi>which could not pleaſe him,</hi> he injured that Action by which he offered up himſelf upon the Croſs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24.</note> that when he <hi>continues to appear before God for us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26.</note> he weakens that Oblation, <hi>by which he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared once,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.</note> 
                  <hi>by the immolation of himſelf;</hi> and that <hi>not ceaſing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49682:34"/>for us,</hi> he accuſes of inſufficiency that interceſſion which he made in dying with <hi>ſo many tears, and ſuch an exclamation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>All this would be ridiculous. We muſt therefore underſtand, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> who once offered up himſelf to be the humble Victim of the Divine Juſtice, does not ceaſe to offer up himſelf always for us; that the infinite perfection of the Sacrifice of the Croſs conſiſts in this, that whatſoever preceded it, as well as what follows it, has an entire reference to it: that as what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded it, was a preparation to it; ſo that which follows it, is the conſummation and application of it: that in reality the payment of the price of our Redemption is no more reiterated, becauſe it was fully diſcharged the firſt time; but that what applies that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption to us continues without ceaſing; that laſtly, we muſt make a diſtinction betwixt thoſe things which are reiterated as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, and thoſe which are continued as perfect and neceſſary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XVI.</hi> Reflections upon the preceding Doctrine.</head>
               <p>WE conjure all thoſe of the Pretended Reformation, to make ſome little Reflection upon what has been ſaid concerning the Euchariſt.</p>
               <p>The Doctrine of the Real Preſence has been the neceſſary foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of it. This Foundation is impugned by the <hi>Calviniſts.</hi> There is nothing appears more important than this in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies; ſeeing the Queſtion is concerning the real Preſence of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> himſelf. There is nothing our Adverſaries find more difficult to believe. And there is nothing in which we are ſo directly oppoſite, as in this.</p>
               <p>In moſt other Diſputes, when theſe Gentlemen hear us with Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they find the difficulties to vaniſh, and that they are more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with words, than with the things themſelves. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, upon this Subject, we agree more about the manner of ſpeaking; becauſe both ſides uſe the words of <hi>Real Participation,</hi> and the like: But the fuller we explicate our ſelves, the more we find our ſelves oppoſed; becauſe our Adverſaries do not receive all the conſequences of thoſe truths which they admit, being diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged (as I ſaid) by the difficulties which Sence and Human Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon find in theſe conſequences.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:49682:35"/>
This is therefore, to ſpeak truly, the moſt difficult of all our Controverſies, and that in which we are the moſt oppoſite to one another.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs God has permitted the <hi>Lutherans</hi> ſhould adhere to the belief of the real Preſence as well as we: and he has alſo permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> ſhould declare this Doctrine to have no poiſon in it; that it does not ſubvert the foundations of Salvation and Faith; and that it ought not to break communion betwixt Brethren.</p>
               <p>Let thoſe of the Pretended Reform'd Religion, who think ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of their Salvation, render themſelves here attentive to that Order, which the Divine Providence makes uſe of to bring them inſenſibly nearer to us and Truth. One may either intirely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipate all the other grounds of their complaints, or at leaſt reduce them to very few Heads, with a little explication. In this, where we cannot hope to conquer by this Method, they have themſelves removed the chief difficulty, by declaring this Doctrine to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nothing in it contrary to Salvation, or to the fundamentals of Religion.</p>
               <p>It is true, the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> tho they concur with us in the ground of the reality, yet admit not all the conſequences of it. They put Bread together with the Body of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST;</hi> ſome of them reject the Adoration; and they ſeem to acknowledg the real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence only in the Act of receiving. But all the ſubtilty of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters can never perſwade ingenuous and underſtanding Perſons, but that, if they maintain the real Preſence, which is the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, and the moſt difficult point they ought alſo to maintain the reſt.</p>
               <p>Moreover the ſame Providence, which labours ſecretly for our nearer Union, and lays the foundations of Reconciliation and of Peace in the midſt of Bitterneſs and Diſputes, has farther per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> to allow, that ſuppoſing theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> ought to be taken in a literal ſence, <hi>Catholics</hi> reaſon better and more conſequently than the <hi>Lutherans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I relate not the paſſages which have been ſo often cited on this account, I hope I ſhall eaſily be excuſed, becauſe all thoſe, who are not obſtinate, will grant us without difficulty, that the reeal Preſence being ſuppoſed, our Doctrine is that which moſt naturally follows.</p>
               <p>It is then an eſtabliſhed Truth, that our Doctrine in this point contains nothing but the real Preſence rightly underſtood. But
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49682:35"/>we muſt not ſtop there; and we beſeech the Pretended Reformed to conſider, we make uſe of no other things to explicate the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Euchariſt, but only ſuch as are neceſſarily included in this reality of preſence.</p>
               <p>If it ſhould be asked us after this, how it comes then to paſs the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> who believe the real preſence, ſhould nevertheleſs reject the Sacrifice, which is, according to us, only a conſequence of it: our anſwer is in one word, that this Doctrine muſt be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the other conſequences of the real preſence, which theſe <hi>Lutherans</hi> have not underſtood, and which we have penetrated much better then they, as the <hi>Calvinists</hi> themſelves confeſs.</p>
               <p>If our Explications perſuade theſe laſt, that our doctrine about the Sacrifice is included in that of the real preſence, they ought to ſee clearly that this mighty diſpute of the Sacrifice of the Maſs, which has filled ſo many Volumes, and occaſioned ſo many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives, ought from henceforwards to be retrenched from the body of their controverſies, becauſe this point has not now any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular difficulty, and (which is much more important) becauſe this Sacrifice, againſt which they have ſo great repugnance, is no other but a neceſſary conſequence and a natural explication of a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which, according to them, has no venom in it. Let them now examin themſelves, and after this, try before God whether they have ſo much reaſon, as they imagine, to withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from thoſe Altars, where their fore-fathers received the Bread of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XVII.</hi> Communion under both kinds.</head>
               <p>THere remains one other Conſequence of this doctrine to be examined, which is, that <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> being really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Sacrament, The Grace and Benediction is not annexed to the ſenſible ſpecies, but to the proper ſubſtance of his fleſh, which is living, and life-giving, becauſe of the Divinity which is united to it. Upon which account, all thoſe, who believe the real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, ought not to have any difficulty to communicate under one ſole ſpecies, becauſe they there receive all that is eſſential to this Sacrament, together with a plenitude ſo ſecure, becauſe there being now no real ſeperation betwixt the Body and the Blood, (as hath
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49682:36"/>been ſaid) we receive entirely, and without diviſion him, who is ſolely capable to ſatiate us.</p>
               <p>This is the ſolid foundation, upon which the Church, interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the precept of Communion, as declared, we may receive the Sanctification, which this Sacrament carries with it, under one ſole ſpecies, and if ſhe have reduced her Children to this ſole ſpecies; it was not out of diſeſteem of the other, ſeeing, on the contrary, ſhe did it to hinder thoſe Irreverences, which the confuſion and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of people had occaſioned in theſe later ages, reſerving to her ſelf, the re-eſtabliſhment of communion under both kinds, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it ſhould become more advantagious to Peace and Unity.</p>
               <p>Catholic Divines have made it appear to thoſe of the pretended Reformation, that they have themſelves made uſe of ſeveral ſuch like Interpretations, in what belongs to the uſe of the Sacrament; but above all they had reaſon to remark this which is taken out of the 12 <hi>chap.</hi> of their diſcipline, Title of the Lords Supper, <hi>art.</hi> 7. where we find theſe words: <hi>The Bread of the Lords Supper ought to be adminiſtred to thoſe who cannot drink wine, upon their making pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, that it is not out of contempt, and endeavouring what they can poſſibly, to obviate all Scandal even by approaching the cup as neer their mouths as they are able.</hi> They have judged, by this regulation that both ſpecies were not, by the inſtitution of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> eſſential to the Communion: otherwiſe they ought to have abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely refuſed the Sacrament to thoſe, who could not receive it whole and entire, and not to give it them after a manner contrary to that which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> had commanded; in which caſe their diſability would have been their excuſe. But our adverſaries conceived it would be an exceſſive rigour, not to allow at leaſt one of the ſpecies to thoſe, who could not receive the other; and as this condeſcendence has no ground in Scripture, they muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with us, the words, by which <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> propoſes to us the two ſpecies, are liable to ſome interpretation, and that this interpretation ought to be declared by the authority of the Church.</p>
               <p>But it might ſeem as if this article of their diſcipline, which was made in the Synod of <hi>Poitiers</hi> held in the year 1560, had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Synod of <hi>Vertueil</hi> held in the year 1567. where it is ſaid <hi>the company is not of opinion, the bread ſhould be adminiſtred to thoſe who would not receive the Cup.</hi> Theſe two Synods neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs are no ways oppoſite. That of <hi>Vertueil</hi> ſpeaks only of thoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49682:36"/>
                  <hi>who will not receive the Cup;</hi> And that of <hi>Poitiers</hi> of theſe only <hi>who cannot.</hi> In effect, notwithſtanding the Synod of <hi>Vertueil,</hi> this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle remains in their diſcipline, and has been alſo approved by a latter Synod then that of <hi>Vertueil,</hi> by the Synod of <hi>la Rochell</hi> in 1571, where this article was review'd, and put into that ſtare in which it now is.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing the Synods of the pretended reform'd Religion had differed in their ſentiments, it would only follow that the matter in queſtion regards not Faith, and that it is of the number of thoſe, which are at the Churches diſpoſal according to their own Principles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XVIII.</hi> The written and unwritten Word.</head>
               <p>THERE remains nothing more now, but to explicate what Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics believe touching the Word of God, and the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> having laid the Foundation of his Church by Preaching, the unwritten Word was the firſt Rule of Chriſtianity; and when the Writings of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> were added, this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written Word did not upon that account loſe its Authority: which makes us reiceive with equal veneration all that was ever taught by the Apoſtles, whether by Writing, or byword of Mouth, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf has expreſly declared. And it is a moſt certain ſign,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.14.</note> a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine comes from the Apoſtles, when it is univerſally embraced by all Chriſtian Churches, without any poſſibility of ſhewing its beginning. We cannot chuſe but receive all that is eſtabliſhed after this manner, with the ſubmiſſion due to Divine Authority; and we are perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thoſe of the Pretended Reformation, who are not obſtinate, are in the bottom of their Hearts of the ſame Opinion; it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to believe a Doctrine, received from the beginning of the Church, can flow from any other ſource than that of the Apoſtles. Wherefore our Adverſaries ought not to wonder if we, who are careful to gather together all our Fathers have left us, ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>Depoſitum</hi> of Tradition as well as that of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:49682:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIX.</hi> The Authority of the Church.</head>
               <p>THE Church being eſtabliſhed by God to be the Guardian of Scripture and Tradition, we receive the Canonical Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from her; and let our Adverſaries ſay what they will, we doubt not but it is her Authority which principally determines them to reverence as Divine Books, the <hi>Canticle</hi> of <hi>Canticles,</hi> which has ſo few viſible marks of a Prophetical Inſpiration; the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of St. <hi>James,</hi> which <hi>Luther</hi> rejected; and that of St. <hi>Jude,</hi> which might appear ſuſpected becauſe of ſome Apocriphal Books cited in it. In fine, it can only be from this Authority they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the whole Body of Scripture, which all Chriſtians accept as Divine, before their reading of it has made them ſenſible of the Spirit of God in it.</p>
               <p>Being then inſeparably bound, as we are, to the Holy Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Church, by means of the Scriptures which we receive from her Hands, we learn Tradition alſo from her; and by the means of Tradition we learn the true ſence of Scripture. Upon which account the Church profeſſes, ſhe tells us nothing from her ſelf, and that ſhe invents nothing new in her Doctrine: ſhe does nothing but declare the Divine Revelation, by the interiour di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Holy Ghoſt, who is given to her as her teacher.</p>
               <p>That Diſpute, which was raiſed in the very time of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, upon account of the Ceremonies of the Law, ſhews clearly, that the Holy Ghoſt explicates himſelf by the Church; and their Acts have by the method by which that firſt Conteſt was decided, taught all ſucceeding Ages, by what Authority all other differences are to be ended. So that as often as there ſhall happen any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes to cauſe a Diviſion amongſt the Faithful, the Church will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe her Authority, and her Paſtors aſſembled will ſay after the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 15.28.</note> 
                  <hi>It his ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and to us.</hi> And when ſhe has ſpoken, her Children will be taught, they ought not to begin again to examine thoſe Articles once ſo reſolved on; but are bound humbly to receive her Deciſions, In this we ſhall follow the example of St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> who carried this firſt Sentence of the Apoſtles to the Faithful, and were ſo far from permitting a new Diſcuſſion of what had been decided, that on the contrary,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49682:37"/>
                  <hi>They went from place to place,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 16.4.</note> 
                  <hi>teaching them to obſerve the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus it is the Children of God acquieſs in the Judgment of the Church, believing that from her Mouth they hear the Oracle of the Holy Ghoſt; and upon account of this belief it is, that after having ſaid in our Creed, <hi>I believe in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> we add im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, <hi>The Holy Catholic Church:</hi> by which we oblige our ſelves to acknowledg an infallible and perpetual verity in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, becauſe this very Church which we believe exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent in all Ages, would ceaſe to be the Church, if ſhe ceaſed to teach the truth revealed by God. So that thoſe who apprehend leaſt ſhe ſhould abuſe her Power to eſtabliſh a Lye, have no Faith in him by whom ſhe is governed.</p>
               <p>And if our Adverſaries would but look upon theſe things in a more mild and candid manner, they would be obliged to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, the Catholic Church is ſo far from making her ſelf Miſtreſs of her Faith, as they have accuſed her, that on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, ſhe has done what ſhe could to bind, and deprive herſelf of all the means of Innovation, ſeeing ſhe not only ſubmits her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Holy Scriptures, but to the end ſhe might for ever baniſh all arbitrary Interpretations, which make Mens Imaginations paſs for Scripture, ſhe has obliged herſelf to interpret them, in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to Faith and Manners,<note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> according to the ſence of the Holy Fathers; from which ſhe proſeſſeth never to depart; declaring in all her Councils, and (in all the Profeſſions of Faith ſhe has pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed) that ſhe does not receive any Doctrine, which is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Tradition of all preceding Ages.</p>
               <p>Moreover, if our Adverſaries conſult their Conſciences, they will find the name of the Church has more Authority over them, than they dare avouch in their diſputes: and I do not think there is any one Prudent Man amongſt them, who finding himſelf the only Perſon of a Perſwaſion, tho it appeared to him never ſo Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, but would abhor that Singularity; ſo true it is, that Men have need in theſe matters to be ſupported in their Tenets, by the Authority of ſome Society, that is, of the ſame opinion with them. And for this reaſon, God who created us, and who knows what is moſt proper for us, hath ordained for our Good, that all Particulars ſhould be ſubject to the Authority of his Church, which of all other Authorities, is without doubt the beſt Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In effect, it is eſtabliſhed not only by that Teſtimony, which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49682:38"/>God himſelf gives of it in the Holy Scriptures, but alſo by the marks of his divine Protection, which are no leſs viſible in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable and perpetual ſubſiſtence of it, than in its miraculous E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XX.</hi> The Sentiments of thoſe of the Pretended Reform'd Religion, concerning the Authority of the Church.</head>
               <p>THIS Supream Authority of the Church is ſo neceſſary to regulate the differences, which ariſe in matters of Faith, and about the Senſe of Scripture, that our Adverſaries themſelves, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having decryed it, as an unſupportable Tyranny, have been at laſt obliged to eſtabliſh it amongſt themſelves.</p>
               <p>When thoſe who are called Independents, declared openly, that each one of the Faithful ought to follow the light of his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, without ſubmitting his Judgment to the Authority of any Body, or Eccleſiaſtical Aſſembly, and upon this Ground refuſed to ſubmit toany Synods; That of <hi>Charenton</hi> held 1644. cenſured this Doctrine upon the ſame Reaſons, and for the ſame Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, for which we reject it. This Synod obſerves in the firſt place, that this Error of the Independents conſiſts in this, that they teach, <hi>Every Church ought to be governed by her proper Laws, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a dependance upon any Perſon in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Obligation to acknowledg the Authority of Conferences and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods for her regulation and conduct.</hi> After which this Synod deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, that <hi>this Sect is a prejudicial to the State as to the Church, that it opens a door to all ſorts of Irregularities and Extravagancies; that it takes away all the means of applying any remedy to it; and that if it took place, there might be as many Religions framed as Pariſhes or particular Aſſemblies.</hi> Theſe laſt words ſhew it is principally in matters of Faith, this Synod would eſtabliſh a <hi>Dependance;</hi> ſeeing the greateſt Inconvenience into which it obſerves the faithful would fall by an Independence, is, <hi>that there might chance to be as many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions formed as Pariſhes.</hi> Every Church then (according to the Doctrine of this Synod) and much more every private Perſon, muſt neceſſarily depend, in what concerns matters of Faith, upon ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperior Authority, which reſides in ſome Aſſembly, or in ſome Body; to which Authority all the Faithful ſubmit their Judgments.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49682:38"/>For the Independents do not refuſe to ſubmit to the Word of God, according as they think it ought to be underſtood; nor to accept the deciſions of Synods, when, after having examined them, they judg them reaſonable. What they refuſe to do is to ſubmit their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to that of any Aſſembly for its ſake; becauſe our Adverſaries have taught them, that every Aſſembly, even that of the Univerſal Church is a Society of men, ſubject to Error, and to which by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence a Chriſtian ought not to ſubmit his Judgment, that ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being only due to God. From this pretention of the Independents it is, thoſe inconveniences follow, which the Synod of <hi>Charenton</hi> ſo well obſerved. For let a man make what Profeſſion he pleaſeth to ſubmit himſelf to the word of God, if every one think he has a right to interpret it according to his own Senſe, and againſt the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of the Church declared in her laſt Sentence, this pretention <hi>will open a door to all ſorts of Extravagancies; it will take away all the means of applying a remedy;</hi> becauſe the deciſion of the Church is not a remedy to thoſe, who think themſelves not obliged to ſubmit to it; in fine, it gives way to the <hi>framing as many Religions,</hi> not only <hi>as there are Pariſhes,</hi> but alſo as there are Perſons.</p>
               <p>To avoid theſe inconveniencies, from whence the ruin of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity would follow, the Synod of <hi>Charenton</hi> finds her ſelf obliged to eſtabliſh <hi>a Dependence in Eccleſiaſtical matters,</hi> and that even in Points of Faith; but this dependence will never hinder thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious conſequences which they deſired to prevent, if they do not, with us, eſtabliſh this Maxim, that every particular Church, and much more every particular perſon amongſt the faithful, ought to believe themſelves obliged to ſubmit their private judgment to the Authority of the Church.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee in the 5th. chapter of the diſcipline of the pretended reform'd Religion, under the title of <hi>Conſiſtories, Art.</hi> 31. that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to preſcribe a means to end <hi>debates, which might ariſe upon any point of Doctrine or Diſcipline,</hi> &amp;c. they ordain firſt the Conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory ſhall endeavour <hi>to appeaſe the whole without noiſe, and with all the ſweetneſs of the word of God;</hi> and after having eſtabliſhed a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory, a Conference, and a Provincial Synod, as ſo many diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent degrees of Juriſdiction, coming at laſt to a National Synod, above which, amongſt them, there is no Authority, they ſpeak of it in theſe terms. <hi>There the entire and final reſolution ſhall be given by the word of God, to which if they refuſe to acquieſce in every point, and with an expreſs diſavowing of their errours, they ſhall be cut off from the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49682:39"/>Church.</hi> It is manifeſt thoſe of the pretended Reformation do not attribute the authority of this laſt ſentence to the word of God taken in it ſelf, and without dependence upon the authority of the Church, for tho this word was made uſe of in their firſt Judgements, yet notwithſtanding they permitted an appeal. It is then this word as interpreted by the ſoveragin tribunal of the Church, which gives <hi>this final reſolution, to which whoſoever refuſes to ſubmit in every point,</hi> altho he boaſt he is authorized by the word of God, is no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted but as a proſane perſon who corrupts and abuſes it.</p>
               <p>But the form of thoſe Letters of deputation which were addreſ'd to the Synod of <hi>Vitre</hi> in the year 1617, to be obſerved by the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces when they were to ſend their Deputies to a National Synod, has yet ſomething more expreſs; it is in theſe terms. <hi>We promiſe before God to ſubmit our ſelves to all that ſhall be concluded and reſolved of in your holy Aſſemblis, to obey them, and put them in execution to our utmoſt power, being perſuaded, as we are, that God will preſide in it, and lead you by his holy ſpirit into all Truth and equity, by the rule of his word.</hi> Here the point is not about receiving the reſolution of a Synod, after they have found it to ſpeak according to Scripture; they ſubmit to it even before it is aſſembled; and they do it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are perſuaded <hi>the Holy Ghoſt will preſide in it.</hi> If this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion be only founded upon a human preſumption, can a man in conſcience <hi>promiſe before God to ſubmit to all that ſhall be there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and reſolved of, to obey, and execute them to the utmoſt of his power?</hi> And if this Perſuaſion has its foundation in a certain belief of the aſſiſtance, which the Holy Ghoſt gives to the Church in her final deciſions, Catholics themſelves require no more.</p>
               <p>So that the proceedings of our Adverſaries ſhew them to agree with us in this ſupreme Authority, without which it is impoſſible ever to put an end to any difficulty in Religion; and tho whilſt they were deſirous to caſt of the yoak of obedience, they denied the Faithful to be obliged to ſubmit their Judgments to that of the Church, yet the neceſſity of eſtabliſhing an order, has ſince forced them to grant what their firſt undertakings had made them deny.</p>
               <p>They have gone yet much further in the National Synod held at <hi>Saint Foy</hi> in the year 1578. There was ſome overture made of a Reconcilement with the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> by means of <hi>a general form of a profeſſion of Faith common to all their Churches,</hi> which was propoſed to be drawn up. Thoſe of this Kingdom were invited to ſend to an Aſſembly, which was to be held upon this account, <hi>Vertuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, authoriſed by all the ſaid Churches, with an ample Procuration,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49682:39"/>TO TREAT; AGREE UPON, AND DECIDE ALL POINTS OF DOCTRINE, <hi>and other matters concerning that union.</hi> Upon this Propoſall, ſee in that terms the reſolution of the Synod of St. <hi>Foy</hi> was couched. <hi>The National Synod of this Kingdom, after having given God thanks for ſuch an overture, and commended the care, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and good advice of the forementioned perſons convocated, and</hi> APPROVING THE REMLDIES WHICH THEY HAVE SUGGESTED, that is to ſay principally that of framing a new Confeſſion of Faith, and to give power to ſome certain perſons to compoſe, it, <hi>has ordained, That if the copy of the above named Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith be ſent in time, it ſhall be examined in each Provincial Synod, or otherwiſe, according to the convenience of each Province; and in the mean time has deputed four Min ſters, the moſt experienced in thoſe affairs, to whom expreſs charge has been given to be preſent at the place and day appointed, with the Letters and full Procurations of all the Miniſters, and Elders, Deputies of the Provinces of this Kingdom, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Lord Viſcount</hi> Turenne, <hi>to do all things above ſaid: yea even, incaſe that</hi> MEANS COULD NOT BE FOUND OUT TO EXAMINE IN EVERY PROVINCE THE SAID CONFES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SION, <hi>it ſhould be referred to their prudence and ſound judgement to agree and</hi> CONCLUDE <hi>all the points which ſhall be brought into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, as well</hi> FOR DOCTRINE, <hi>as for other matters concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the benefit, union, and peace of all the Churches.</hi> It was to this, in fine, that this ſeeming tenderneſs of Conſcience of theſe pretended Reformes tended. How often have they reproched to us, as a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that ſubmiſſion which we pay to the Deciſions of the Church, which ſay they, is nothing elſe but a company of men lyable to error? and yet nevertheleſs, being aſſembled in a Body in a National Synod, which repreſented all the Churches of the pretended Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>France,</hi> they are not afraid, by mutual conſent, to leave their faith to the arbitration of four men, with ſo abſolute an abandoning of their own ſentiments, that they gave them full power to change the very Confeſſion of Faith it ſelf, which they do at this very day propoſe to the whole Chriſtian world as a Confeſſion of Faith, which containeth nothing but the pure Word of God, and for which, as they ſaid in preſenting it to our Kings, an infinite number of people were ready to ſhed their Blood. I leave the prudent Reader to make his reflections upon the Decree of this Synod; and ſhall in a few words finiſh the Explication of the Churches Tenets.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49682:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XXI.</hi> The Authority of the Holy See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Son of God, being deſirous his Church ſhould be one, and and ſolidly built upon Unity, hath eſtabliſhed and inſtituted the Primacy of St. <hi>Peter</hi> to maintain and cement it. Upon which account, we acknowledg this Primacy in the <hi>Succeſſors</hi> of the Prince of the Apoſtles, to whom, for this cauſe, we owe that Obedience and Submiſſion, which the Holy Councils and Fathers have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways taught the faithful.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe things, which we know are diſputed of in the Schools, tho the Miniſters continually alledg them to render this Power odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, it is not neceſſary we ſpeak of them here, ſeeing they are not Articles of the Catholic Faith. It is ſufficient we acknowledg a Head eſtabliſhed by God to conduct his whole flock in his paths; which thoſe who love Concord amongſt Brethren, and Eccleſiaſtical Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, will moſt willingly acknowledg.</p>
               <p>And certainly if the Authors of the Pretended Reformation had loved Unity, they would neither have aboliſhed Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was eſtabliſhed by <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> himſelf, and which we find in force even in the times of the Apoſtles; nor have deſpiſed the Authority of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, which has ſo ſolid a Foundation in the Goſpel, and ſo evident a ſucceſſion in Tradition; but they would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have carefully conſerved Epiſcopal Authority, which eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unity in particular Churches, and the Primacy of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, which is the common Center of all Catholic Unity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XXII.</hi> Concluſion of this Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>THIS is the Expoſition of the Catholic Doctrine, in which, that I might tye my ſelf to the moſt principal, I have left ſome queſtions untouched, which thoſe of the Pretended Reform'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion do not look upon as lawful matter for a Separation. I hope thoſe of their Communion, who ſhall impartially examin all the Parts of this Treatiſe, will be better diſpoſed by the reading of it, to give ear to thoſe proofs upon which the Faith of the Church is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49682:40"/>and will in the mean time acknowledg many of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies may be ended by a ſincere explication of our Tenets; that her Doctrine is Holy, and that, according to their own Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, no one of her Articles deſtroys the grounds of Salvation.</p>
               <p>If any one ſhould think fit to anſwer this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> he is deſired to conſider, that to accompliſh his intent, he muſt not undertake to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the Doctrine contained in it, ſeeing my Deſign was only to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, without going about to prove it; and that if in ſome Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I have hinted at ſome of the reaſons which eſtabliſh it, it is becauſe the knowledg of the principal reaſons of a Doctrine, is often a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary part of it's Explication.</p>
               <p>It would alſo be a quitting of the deſign of this Treatiſe, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min the different methods, which Catholic Divines make uſe of to eſtabliſh or explicate the Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and the different Conſequences, which particular Doctors have drawn from it. To urge any thing ſolid againſt this Treatiſe, and which may come home to the point; it muſt be proved that the Churches Faith is not here faithfully expounded, and that by Acts which the ſame Church has obliged herſelf to receive; or elſe it muſt be ſhown, that this Explication leaves all the Objections in their full force, and all the Diſputes untouched; or, in fine, it muſt be preciſely ſhown in what this Doctrine ſubverts the Foundations of Faith.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="ita" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:49682:41"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49682:41"/>
            <head>Lettre de Monſeigneur le Cardinal BONA a Monſeigneur le Card. de BUILLON.</head>
            <p>HO ricevnto il libro di Monſignor Veſcovo di Condom, che V. E. ſi è degnata inviarmi, e sì come Conoſco la qualità del favore, em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne pregio, coſi rendo alla ſua gentilezza infinite gratie e per il dono e per il penſiero che ſi pronde di acoreſcere la mia Libraria. L'hò letto con at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentione particolare, e perche V E. mi accenna che alcuni lo accuſano di qualche mancamento, hò voluto particolarmente oſſervare in che poteſſe eſſer ripreſo. Mà realmente non sò trovarci ſe non materia di grandiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma lode, perche ſenza entrare nelle queſtioni ſpinoſe delle controverſie, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>una maniera ingegnoſa, facile, e famigliare, e con metodo, per così dire, geometrica da certi principii communi &amp; approvati convince i Calveniſti, e li neceſſita à conſeſſare la verità della Fede Cattolica. Aſſicuro V. E. di haverlo letto con mia indicibile ſodisfattione; nè mi maraviglio che<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gli habbino trovato à dire, perche tutte le Opere grandi, e che ſormonta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no l'ordinario, ſempre hanno contradittori. Vince però finalmente la ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rità, e da'frutti ſi conoſce la qualità dell'albero. Me ne rallegre con l' Autore, il quale hà dato ſaggio del ſuo gran talento con queſta a opera, e potrà con molte altre ſervire lodevolmente à Santa Chieſa.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Roma <date>
                     <hi>19.</hi> Gennaro <hi>1672.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="ita" type="letter">
            <head>Lettre de Monſeigneur le Cardinal SIGISMOND CHIG la Monſieur L'Abbé de DANGEAU.</head>
            <p>RICEVEI con la ſua lettera ill Libro della Eſpoſitione della Dottrina Cattolica del Veſcovo di Condom, molto erudito e molto utile per convertire gl heretici più con le vive ragioni, che con l'aſprezza del diſcorſo. Parlai al Padre Maſtro di S. Palazzo, &amp; al Segretario dell' Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne dell Indice, e conobbi veramente, che non viera ſtato chi haveſſe a queſti Padri parlato in disfavore del medeſimo. Anzi li trovai pieni di eſtimatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne per il medeſimo: &amp; havendo poi parlato con queſti Signori Cardinali della Congregatione, trovai frà gl'altri il Signor Cardinale Brancaccio molto inclinato a pregiarlo, e molto propenſo a lodarne l'Autore. Onde io tengo certo che qua ancora Monſignor di Condom ottenga quella lode,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49682:42"/>che e dovuta alla ſua fatica &amp; alla ſua dottrina. Reſto per tanto obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gato alla ſua gentilezza che mi ha dato modo di ammirar la medeſima; mentre mi pare che l'Autore ſtring a bene i ſuoi argomenti, e moſtri chiaro i punti nei quali i diviſi diſcordano della Chieza; ne credo che il modo che tien l'Autore, ſia da condannarſi nell'eſplicatione di qualche Dottri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na inſegnata dal Concilio di Trento, eſſendo praticato da molti Scrittori &amp; eſſendo da lui maneggiato molto regolatamente; in oltre che l'Autore non ha havuto in mente d'inte pretare i dogmi di quel Concilio; ma ſolo importarlinel ſuo libro eſplicati perche gl'heretici reſtino convinti, &amp; in chiaro di tutto quello che la Santa Chieſa gl'obliga di credere. Dell'auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita del Papa, ne parlabene, e con il dovnto riſpetto della Sede Romana ogni voliàche parla del capo viſibile della Chieſa; onde torno à dire che non e capace che di lode.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Roma <date>
                     <hi>5.</hi> Aprile <hi>1672.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="ita" type="letter">
            <head>Lettre du Reverendiſſ. Pere HYACINTHE LIBELLI, alors Maiſtre du Sacre Palais, &amp; maintenant Archeveſque d'Avignon, a Monſeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur le Cardinal SIGISMOND CHIGI.</head>
            <p>HO letto il Libro del Sig. di Condom continente l'Eſpoſitione dellae Dottrina della Chieſa. Devo infinite gratie à V. E. che mi habbia fatte conſumare quattro hore di tempo sì virtuo ſamente, e con tanto mio di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letro. Mi è piacciuto ſopra modo, e per l'Argomento ſingolare, e per le pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve, che à quello correſpondono. La Dottrina è tutta ſana ne v'ha embra di mancamento. No per me sò quello che poſſa opporviſi; e ſe l'Autore deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reràche ſi riſtamp: in Roma, da me otterrà totte le facoltà che gli ſaranno neceſſarie ad effetto che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſi riſtampi ſenſa mutarne ne pure una parola. L'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore che ha molto ingegno ſi è ſervito in queſta operetta del giuditio, perche laciate da parte le diſpute, che ſogliono quaſi ſempre accreſcer le diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, trovandoſi di rai o chi voglia cedere le prerogative del ingegno al compagno, hà trovato un 'altro modo più facile di trattar co'Calviniſti dal quale puo ſperarſi maggior frutto. Perche ogni volta che perdin quel orrore à noſtri dogmi che hanno ſucchiato col latte, à noi più volentieri s'accoſtano, e poſta in mala fede la dottrina che hanno appreſa da loro Maſtri di cui la maſſima principale è eſſere i noſtri dogmi orrendi &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credili, ſi pongono con minor paſſion d'animo à cercar la verità Cattolica,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49682:42"/>che è quello a che devono eſortarſi acciccche rineghino gli errori, perche, come V. E. diſcorreva l'atro gierno, la verità Cattolica vince appreſſo ogn' huemo prudente riconoſciuta à petto dell'Ereſia agni volta che ſia eſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minata ſenza preoccupatione di ſpirito. Hò preſo ardire di fare à V. E. queſta lunga diceria per una sfogo del contento ch' hò havnto di legere il ſudetto libro, che Ella hà fatto gratia di participarmi, e pregandòla a continuarmi ſimili favori le baci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> riverentemente le veſti.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Roma <date>
                     <hi>26.</hi> Aprile <hi>1672.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="letter">
            <head>Illuſtriſſimo &amp; Reverendiſſimo Domino JACO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BO BENIGNO Epiſc. Condomenſi S. P. D. FERDINANDOS Epiſcop. &amp; Princeps Pader<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornenſis Coad. Monaſterienſis.</head>
            <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ANQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AM ad virtutem as eruditionem tuam toti terrarum or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi omnique poſteritati commendandam ſufficiat judicium Regis Christianiſſimi, qui filium ſuum in ſpem tantae genitum tibi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituendum erudiendumque commiſit: tu tamen immortali proprii ingenii monimento, aureo videlicet illo libello, cui titulus eſt, <hi>Expoſitio Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina Eccleſiae Catholicae,</hi> nomen tuum pariterque Chriſtianam diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinam magis illuſtrare voluiſti; coque non ſolum ab omnibus Catholicis maximos plauſiu tuliſſi, ſed etiam ex ipſis heterodoxis veriſſimas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genii atque doctrine tuae landes expreſſiſti. Elucet enim in admirabili illo opuſculo incredibilis quaedam res difficiles &amp; planè caeleſtes atque di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinas explicandi facilitas, &amp; gratiſſimus candor, ac verè Chriſtiana Charitas atque Benignitas, qua ſedentes in tenebris &amp; umbra mortis taw ſuaviter allicis, &amp; illuminas, ac dirigis in viam pacis, ut unus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporum ad hoſtes Catholicae fidei ſub jugum ſuave veritatis mittendos fictus &amp; factus eſſe videaris. Quapropter ut eximii operis fructus lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giùs manaret, atque per univerſam Germaniam, aliaſque gentes ſeſe diffunderet, libellum tuum in latinum ſermonem convertendi impetum cepi; ſed ubi literas tuas VIII. Cal. Maii datas perlegi, dubitavi ſanè utrùm progredi oporteret, an incepto abſiſtere, quia te non ſolum Gallici, ſed ctiam Latini ſermonis nitore ac elegantiâ tantopere pollere perſpexi, ut quicunque praeter temetipſum tua ſcripta de Gallico verteret, is pulcheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ingenii tui partum deformaturus potius, quàm ornaturus eſſe vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur. Quarè tu potiſſimùm eſſes orandus, ut foetum, quem in lucem
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49682:43"/>edidiſti, latinitate donares. Sed quia forſitan id tibi per occupationes non licet, &amp; ſiquidem tantum tibi ſit otii, obſecrandus es potiùs, ut plura ſcribas, quàm ut ſcripta convertas; faciam id quod tibi pergra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſſe ſignificas, &amp; illum cui hanc provinciam dedi urgebo, ut inchoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta perficiat; tibique verſionem libelli tui cenſendam corrigendamque tranſmittam. Te verò, Praeſul Illuſtriſſime longéque doctiſſime, maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mopere ſemper obſervabo &amp; amicitiam tuam ad quam hic meus conatus &amp; tua benignitas aditum mihi patefecit, omni officie colere ſtudebo. Vale, antiſtes eximie, ac de Republicâ Chriſtianâ optimè merite, &amp; me, ut facias, ama, atque Sereniſſimo Delphino cum optimis artibus atque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis noſtram quoque memoriam &amp; amorem inſtilla, &amp; Ducem Montau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerium meis verbis jube ſalvere plurimùm.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>In Arce meâ ad Confluentes Luppiae, Paderae &amp; Aliſonis, <date>
                     <hi>3.</hi> Kal. Jun. <hi>1673.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="ita" type="letter">
            <head>Lettre du Reverendiſſ. Pere RAIMOND CAPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUCCHI Maiſtre du Sacré Palais, a L'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teur.</head>
            <p>IL merito ſublime di V. S. Ill. da me ammirato, doveva eſſe ranche ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vito nell'occaſione del dottiſſimo, &amp; eruditiſſimo libro da lei compoſto in difeſa della Fede Cattolica, &amp; tradotto per beneficio di tutti anche nella Lingua Italiana; onde io devo render ſingolariſſime gratie, come faccio à V. S. Ill. dell'occaſione, che mi hà dato di ſervirla. Stiamo tutti at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo la publicatione di queſto belliſſimo libro, per godere delle ſue nobiliſſime fatiche, &amp; io in particolare che vivo, e vivero ſempre ambitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo di al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ri ſuoi commandamenti, e qui per fine con ogni oſſequio la rive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſco.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Roma <date>
                     <hi>20.</hi> Guign. <hi>1675.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbations">
            <head>Approbations de l'Edition Romaine de 1678.</head>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="approbation">
               <head>Approvatione del Signor MICHEL ANGELO RICCI, Segret. della S. Congr. dell' Indulgenze e S. Reliq. e Conſultore del S. Offitio.</head>
               <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>OD Tridentina Synodus magno ſtudio aſſecuta eſt, ut doctrinam Fidei ab opinionibus, &amp; controverſus inter Catholices om unò ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneret,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49682:43"/>ac candem apertiùs, &amp; ſignificantiùs explicaret; ac Tertullianus olim, ut Hareticorum ſeceſſionem ab Eccleſia certis praeſcriptionibus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probaret; alii, ut principia quaedam Haereticorum, &amp; regulas, ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futationem ipſerum ingeniosè contorquerent: ea Clariſſimus quoque Vir Jacobus Benignus Boſſuet, Condomi Epiſcopus, praeſtitit in hoc Opere, perſpicua methodo, brevi, &amp; ad perſuadendum accommodata, quae qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem praeclarum Auctoris ingenium refert. Quod Opus Italorum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditati nunc eleganter verſum è Gallica in maternam linguam praelo, ac luce dignum exiſtimo.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Romae <date>die <hi>5.</hi> Auguſti <hi>1678.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>MICHAEL ANGEL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S RICCI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="approbation">
               <head>Approvatione del P. M. LORENZO BRANCA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TI da LAUREA delle Congr. Conſiſt. Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genze, Riti, Viſita e S. Offit. Conſul. e Qualif. e Pr. Cuſt. della Lib. Vaticana, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CE dignum exiſtimo Opuſculum, ſeu diſcurſum Gallicè &amp; variis linguis impreſſum, nunc autem ex Gallico in Italicum idioma conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, in quo Illuſtriſſimus Dominus Jacobus Benignus Boſſuet Epiſcopus &amp; Toparca Condomi, nobili, ſed gravi ac ſolido ſtylo Religionis Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſae Reformatae Miniſtros, &amp; Aſſeclas, tam communibus Eccleſiae fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentalibus regulis, quàm propriis corundem principiis fortiter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringit, oſtendens, non Catholicos, ut ii Miniſtri autumant, ſed ipſoſmet Miniſtros, per improp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ias conſequentias receſſiſſe ab Eccleſiae dogmatibus, nobis, ipſiſque communibus; &amp; ex pravis ejuſmodi Scripturae vel Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum intelligentiis, Catholicam communionem reliquiſſe. Et ſi ipſi Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtri Catholicorum Regulas in Conciliis, praeſertim in Tridentino funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, abſque paſſione ſerutarentur, proculdubio, ex Dei auxilio, ad ſanctam redirent unitatem; &amp; diſcurrens per ſingulas controverſias ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viter, ſed palmariè id exequitur.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Datum in Conventu Sanctorum XII. Apoſtolorum. Romae <date>die <hi>25.</hi> Julii <hi>1678.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>F. LA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RENTI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S DE LA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>REA MIN. CONVENT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALIS.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="approbation">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49682:44"/>
               <head>Approbatione del Sign. Abbate STEPHANO GRADI.</head>
               <p>LEGI diligenter, &amp; ſtudiosè egregium ſummi Viri Jacobi Benigni Condoménſis Antiſtitis Opus, in ſermonem Italicum fideliter elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter que converſum, quo Doctrina Eccleſiae breviter, enucleatè, luculenter exponitur. Indeque ſic affectus animo diſceſſi, ut legentes optima quaeque, at que à ſana doctrina, &amp; ſumma ratione optimè parata, ſolent diſcedere, ut non alia ſe dicturos, nec aliter locuturos, ſi ad ſcribendum de tali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſe contuliſſent, exiſtiment. Super omnia verò me cepit Scriptoris, ut it a dicam ſobrietas in delectu rerum, quas promit, dum circumciſis, quae lites extendere, &amp; meliori cauſae invidiam conflare nata ſunt, ipſam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis arcem capeſſit, tutamque, &amp; inacceſſam praeſtat; totus in rectè conſtituendo controverſiae ſtatu, quam ea re dijudicatu facilem, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditam efficit. Hune itaque librum, ſi me audient, quibus concordi Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Chriſtiana, &amp; ſalva ſua ipſorum anima opus eſt, diurna nocturna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que manu verſare non deſinent; neque non fieri poteſt, ne eos diverſa à Fide orthodoxa ſentire non pigeat, pudeatque.</p>
               <closer>Ita ſentio <signed>ego STEPHANUS GRADIUS, S. Congreg. Indicis Conſultor. &amp; Biblioth. Vatic. Praef.</signed>

               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Imprimatur ſi videbitur Reverendiſſ. P. S. P. Apoſt. Magiſtro.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>J. DE ANGELIS, Archiep. Urb. Viceſger.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>F. RAIMUNDUS CAPISUCCUS, Ord. Praed. S. P. A. Magiſter.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="letter">
               <head>Bref De N. S. P. le Pape. INNOCENTIUS PP. XI.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>VEnerabilis Frater, ſalutem &amp; apostolicam benedictionem.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>Libellus de Catholicae Fidei Expoſitione à fraternitate tua compoſitus, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſque oblatus, ea doctrina eaque methodo ac prudentia ſcripius eſt, ut perſpicua brevitate legentes doceat, &amp; extorquere poſſit etiam ab invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Catholicae veritatis confeſſionem. Itaque non ſolùm à nobis commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, ſed ab omnibus legi, at que in pretio haberi meretur. Ex eo ſanè non
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49682:44"/>mediocres in orthodoxae Fidei propagationem, quae nos praecipuè cura in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentos ac ſolicitos habet, utilitates redundatliras, Déo benè juvante, confidimus: ac vetus interim noſtra de tua virtute ac pietate opinio comprobatur, magno cum incremento ſpei jampridem ſuſceptae fore ut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutioni tuae creditus, eximia, hoc eſt paterna, avitaque praeditus indole DELPHIN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, eam à te hauriat diſciplinam, qua maximè informatum eſſe decet Chriſtianiſſimi Regis filium, in quem unà cum florentiſſimo reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, Catholicae Religionis defenſio perventura eſt: idque perenni cum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis ipſius decore, qui Fratermtatem tuam inter tot egregios viros qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Gallia abundat, ad opus potiſſimùm elegit, in quo publicae foelicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis fundamenta jacerentur; cùm divino doceamur Oraculo, patris glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am eſſe filium ſapientem. Tu perge alacriter in incepto, ad quod inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare te, praeter alia, magnoperc debet, qui jam apparet laborum, atque induſtriae tuae fructus. Audimus enim &amp; quidem ex omnium ſermone, ac magno cum animi noſtri ſolatio inter tot prementia mala audimus, DELPHIN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M ipſum magno ad omnem virtutem impetu ferri, &amp; paria pietatis atque ingenii documenta praebere, Illud tibi pro certo affirmamus, nulla in re devincire te arctiùs poſſe paternam noſtram er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga te voluntatem, quàm in regio adoleſcente bonis omnibus, &amp; Rege maximo dignis artibus imbuendo, ut is adulta poſted aetate, Barbaras gentes &amp; Chriſtiani nominis inimicas, quas parentem inclytum reddita Europae pace, &amp; tranſlatis in orientem invictis arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Imperio latè ſuo adjecturum ſperamus, victor &amp; ipſe ſanctiſſimis legibus, moribuſque componat. Devotionem interim atque obſervantiam quam erga ſanctam hanc Sedem, noſque ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, qui in ea Catholicae Eceleſiae immerito praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus, tuae ad nos literae luculenter declarant, mutuae charitatis affectu complectimur, cujus profectò in occaſionibus quae ſe dederint Fratenitati tuae argumenta non deerunt, tibique Apoſtolicam benedictionem pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manter impertimur.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Datum Romae, apud S. Petrum ſub annulo Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris, <date>die IV. Januarii <hi>1679.</hi> Pontificatus noſtri anno <hi>111.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>MARI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S SPIN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LA. </signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>Et au deſſus:</hi> Venerabili Fratri Jacobo, Epiſcopo Condomenſi.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="testimonies">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49682:45"/>
            <head>The <hi>foregoing</hi> Teſtimonies rendred into <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the <hi>French.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter from his E. the Cardinal <hi>BONA</hi> of happy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, to his <hi>E.</hi> the Cardinal <hi>de BUILLON.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have received the R. Biſhop of <hi>Condom's</hi> Book, which your E. did me the Honour to ſend me; and as I am ſenſible of the quallity of this Favour, and eſteem my ſelf much honoured by it; ſo I render you my moſt Cordial thanks, as well for the Preſent, as for the Care you take to encreaſe my Library. I have read it with a particular attention; and becauſe your E. tells me, there are ſome who find ſome fault in it, I endeavour'd expreſly to obſerve in what it might be worthy of reprehenſion. But in effect I could not find any thing in it, but matter of great Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſeeing without entring into the more difficult queſtions in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, he makes uſe of a moſt ingenious, eaſie, and familiar manner, and of a Method, as I may ſay, Geometrical, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> by common and approved Principles, and to force them to confeſs the Catholick Faith.</p>
               <p>I can aſſure your E. I found, in reading it, a Satisfaction which I cannot expreſs; and I am not aſtoniſhed that ſome have found fault with it, for all Works great and above the common Level, find Perſons ſtill to contradict them. But Truth prevails in the End, and the quality of the Tree is known by the Fruit. I congratulate with the Author, who has by this work given us an Eſſay of his great Talents, and may by many others render conſiderable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the Church.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 19th. <hi>January,</hi> 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter from Cardinal <hi>SIGISMOND CHIGI,</hi> of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Memory, to the Abbot of <hi>DANGFAU.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have received, together with your Letter, the Expoſition of the Catholick Doctrine, compos'd by the Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> I have found it full of Erudition, and ſo much the more proper to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49682:45"/>Heretics, as it preſſes them with lively Reaſons, without any Bitterneſs. I made mention of it to the Reverend Father, Maſter of the Sacrod Palace, and to the Secretary of the Congregation <hi>dell' Indice:</hi> I underſtood that no body had ſpoken againſt it to theſe Fathers, who ſeemed to me, on the contrary, full of Eſteem for this Work. I diſcourſed of it likewiſe to the Cardinals of the Congregation, and, amongſt all the reſt, I found Cardinal <hi>Brancas</hi> much enclined to praiſe the Author, and eſteem the Book. So that I doubt not but <hi>M. de Condom</hi> will receive here the ſame appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, which has been given him every where elſe, and which is ſo legitimately due both to his Learning, and his Labour. I am very much obliged to you for having given me the means of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring him, and have perceived in this, your old and ordinary goodneſs. The Author is cloſe in his Proofs, and explicates very clearly the Subject he treats on, in ſhewing the true difference betwixt the belief of Catholics, and that of the Enemies of the Church. I do not think the method he takes, to explicate the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine taught in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> can in the leaſt be diſapprov'd. This Method having been practiſed by many other Writers, and being handled throughout his whole Book, with great Exactneſs. Certainly it was never his Intention to give the Interpretation of the Tenets of the Council, but only to deliver them in his Book, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly explicated, in ſuch ſort that Heretics may be convinc'd, and eſpecially in thoſe things which the Holy Church obliges them to believe. He ſpeakes perfectly well of the Popes Authority, and whereever he treats of the viſible Head of the Church, he appears full of reſpect for the Holy See. In fine, I muſt tell you once again, <hi>M. de Condom</hi> cannot be too much commended, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>April the</hi> 5th. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter from the Reverend Father <hi>HIACINTHUS LIBELLI,</hi> at that time Maſter of the Sacred Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and now Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Avignon,</hi> to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>SIGISMOND CHIGI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have read <hi>M. de Condom</hi>'s Book, which contains an Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Church. I am extreamly indebted to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49682:46"/>your Eminence for giving me the opportunity of employing four hours ſo profitably, and with ſo much Pleaſure. It is impoſſible for me to expreſs how much this work has pleaſed me, both for the peculiar Excellence of the deſign, and for the Proofs which corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond to it. The Doctrine is ſound in all its parts; and without the ſmalleſt ſhadow of a fault. As for my ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I cannot ſee what can be objected againſt it; and if the Author would have the Book Printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> I will give all the neceſſary Approbations, without changing a ſingle Word. This Author, who has a great deal of Wit, has ſhown a great deal of Judgment too in this Treatiſe, where, laying aſide diſputes, which ordinarily ſpeaking do but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Diſſentions, it being rare to find any who will grant the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence of Wit to their Companions, he has found out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and more eaſie, Method of treating with the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> from which much better Fruit may be expected. In effect, as ſoon as they can be brought to lay aſide that horrour which they have ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in with their Milk, againſt our Tenets, they come more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly towards us, and diſcovering the inſincerity of that Doctrine which they learn'd from their Maſters, the principal Maxim of which is, That our Doctrines are horrid and incredible, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves, with more tranquillity of Mind, to ſearch into Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Verities.</p>
               <p>This is what they muſt be carefully exhorted to, ſinee there is no better Method to make them renounce their Errors; and your Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence had great reaſon when you lately ſaid, That Catholic Truth will always be victorious in the Mind of every man of Senſe, who will only without prejudice conſider it in compariſon with Hereſy. I take the Liberty to write this long Diſcourſe to your Eminence, not being able to contain within my ſelf the Pleaſure, which the reading of this Book, you have been pleaſed to let me have, has afforded me. I beg your Eminence will continue the like Favours to me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                     <date>26 <hi>April,</hi> 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49682:46"/>
               <head>A Letter from the Biſhop and Prince of <hi>PADER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BORNE,</hi> at that time Coadjutor, and now Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> to the Author.</head>
               <p>THE moſt Chriſtian King, when he entruſted to you the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Education of his Son, born to ſo much Greatneſs, did by his Judgment alone ſufficiently recommend your Knowledg, and your Merit to all the World, and all Poſterity: yet you have given a new Luſtre to your Reputation, and to the Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, by an immortal Monument of your Worth; I would ſay, by that moſt excellent Book, whoſe Title is, <hi>An Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Catholic Church,</hi> which has not only gained the vaſt applauſe of Catholics, but forced the Heretics themſelves to give deſerved Praiſes to your Judgment, and Erudition. In this moſt admirable Treatiſe, there appears a moſt incredible facility to unfold the moſt difficult, the moſt ſublime, and moſt divine things; and at the ſame time a moſt winning candor, and a tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſtian Charity, and Bounty, capable to draw with ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs all thoſe who are ſet in Darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of Death, and to enlighten, and conduct them into the way of Peace: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that you ſeem to be choſen amongſt the Biſhops, to reduce the Enemies of Catholic Faith under the eaſie Yoak of Truth. To the end therefore the effects of this great work might be the more extended, and might ſpread it ſelf throughout all <hi>Germany,</hi> and amongſt other Nations, I had formed to my ſelf a deſign of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it put into <hi>Latin;</hi> but after having read your Letter of the 24th. of <hi>April,</hi> I had a doubt whether I ought to proceed any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in it, or quit my deſign, becauſe I perceived you were as perfect a Maſter of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, as of the <hi>French;</hi> and that you writ it with ſo much Purity, that if any other ſhould undertake to tranſlate your Works, inſtead of adorning thoſe curious Products of your Wit, he might on the contrary diſcredit them. You ought the rather therefore to be deſired to put your ſelf in <hi>Latin</hi> what you have publiſhed. But ſeeing that perhaps you have not leiſure, and if you had, it would be much better you ſhould be employed in the Compoſition of more new Works, than in the tranſlation of thoſe you have already Compoſed; becauſe you admit of it, I will
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49682:47"/>haſten him, to whom I have committed it, to finiſh what he has begun; and will ſend you the Verſion of your own Book, that you may review and correct it your ſelf. What remains for me, is always infinitely to honour your Vertue and Learning, and to make it my endeavour to cultivate that Friendſhip, which my care of the Verſion, and your Bounty have given ſo favourable a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to. Continue ſtill to love me, moſt worthy Prelate who ſerve the Church ſo well, and while you give the <hi>Dauphin</hi> ſo many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent inſtructions, contrive for me a place in the remembrance and affection of ſo great a Prince. Give, if you pleaſe, my moſt humble Service to the Duke <hi>de Montauſier.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>In my Caſtle, at the confluence of the <hi>Lippe,</hi> the <hi>Padere,</hi> and the <hi>Aliſe,</hi> 
                     <date>the 29th. of <hi>May,</hi> 1673:</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter from the Reverend Father <hi>RAIMUNDUS CAPISUCCHI,</hi> Maſter of the Sacred Palace, to the Author.</head>
               <p>AFter having admired with all others ſo ſublime a deſert as yours; I muſt alſo ſhew the particular Inclination I have to ſerve you, occaſioned by that excellent and learned Work you have compoſed for the defence of the Catholic Faith, and which has been lately tranſlated into <hi>Italian,</hi> for it's farther ſpreading. I am indebted to you an infinite acknowledgment for having af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded me an occaſion of rendring you ſome Service; we are all of us here in great expectation of the publiſhing of this excellent piece, that we may enjoy the fruits of your Labours. No body will have a greater ſatisfaction than my ſelf, who do, and ſhall always feel an ardent deſire to render my ſelf worthy of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your Commands. I end with aſſuring you of my Reſpects.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                     <date>20 <hi>June,</hi> 1675.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="approbations">
            <head>The Approbations of the <hi>Roman</hi> Edition, Anno <hi>1678.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="approbation">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49682:47"/>
               <head>The Approbation of Signor <hi>MICHEL ANGELO RICCI,</hi> Secretary to the Congregation of <hi>I.</hi> and <hi>H. R.</hi> and Conſultor of the Holy Office.</head>
               <p>VVHAT the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> has with great care performed, in making an entire ſeparation betwixt Articles of Faith, opinions, and diſputes of the Schools; and explicating the ſame Doctrines of Faith in more clear and ſignificant Terms; what <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> had formerly done, in condemning the ſeceſſion of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics from the Church by ſeveral Preſcriptions; what others have practiſed, whilſt they ingenuouſly combated Heretics by their own Principles and Rules; the ſame has the Right Reverend <hi>James Benign Boſſuet</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi> performed in this Work, in a clear and ſhort Method, proper to perſwade; manifeſting to us the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable parts of the Author. Which work being now for the convenience of the <hi>Italians,</hi> elegantly tranſlated out of <hi>French,</hi> into our Mother Language, I eſteem worthy to be Printed and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Auguſt the</hi> 5th. 1678.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="approbation">
               <head>The Approbation of the Reverend Father <hi>LAURENCE BRANCATI DE LAUERA</hi> of the Congregat. Conſiſt. of I. Rites, Viſit, Conſultor and Qualificator of the Holy Office, and Bibliothecarian of the Vatican Library, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Eſteem moſt worthy publiſhing the little Treatiſe or Diſcourſe, Printed in <hi>French</hi> and ſeveral other Languages, and at preſent Tranſlated out of <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Italian,</hi> in which the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>James Benign Boſſuet</hi> Biſhop and Lord of <hi>Condom</hi> does force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably combat in a Noble, Grave, and Solid Stile, the Miniſters of the Pretended Reform'd Religion and their followers, as well by the common and fundamental Rules of the Church, as by their own Principles; ſhowing, that it is not Catholics, as thoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49682:48"/>imagine, but the Miniſters themſelves, who by drawing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Conſequences, have receded from thoſe Tenets which are common to them and us, and by taking the Scriptures and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils in a wrong ſenſe, have ſeparated themſelves from the Catholic Church. But if they would examin without paſſion the Rules of Catholics grounded upon their Councils, and eſpecially upon that of <hi>Trent,</hi> they would without doubt, by the Grace of God, return again to a Holy Unity: all which this Author ſhows them in a moſt pleaſing, and no leſs convincing manner, running through all the points of Controverſie.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given in the <hi>Convent</hi> of the Twelve Apoſtles at <hi>Rome,</hi> 
                     <date>the 25. <hi>July,</hi> 1678.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>F. Laurentius de Laurea, Min. Conventualis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="approbation">
               <head>The Approbation of the Abbot <hi>Stephen Gradi.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have with diligence and application read the excellent Work of the Lord <hi>James Benign Boſſuet,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> faithfully and elegantly Tranſlated into <hi>Italian,</hi> where the Doctrine of the Church is explicated after a manner both conciſe, clear, and full. And it wrought the ſame Impreſſion in me, which ordinarily thoſe nobler ſort of Writings, which are the products of a ſound Doctrine and ſolid Reaſon, do in their Readers, when they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd they could not have ſaid any thing more to the purpoſe, nor ſpoken otherwiſe, if they had undertaken to write of the ſame Subject. But what Tranſported me the moſt was that Wiſdom and Moderation of the Author in the choice of thoſe things which he aſſerts; he retrenches all thoſe things which ſerve only to lengthen Diſputes, and render a good Cauſe odious, and betakes himſelf to Truth alone, as to a ſtrong hold, which he renders not only ſecure but inacceſſable: applying himſelf wholly to eſtabliſh the true ſtate of the Queſtion, which by that means is rendred clear and eaſie to be judged of. Upon which account, all thoſe, if they will believe me, who are concerned for the Peace of the Church, or the Salvation of their Souls, ought day and night to turn over this Book; and it is impoſſible, but it ſhould produce in them both ſhame and ſorrow, for holding Tenets, contrary to the Orthodox Faith.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49682:48"/>
               <closer>I am of this Opinion,
<signed>
                     <hi>St. G. Conſultor</hi> of the <hi>Congregation de l' Indice, Prefect</hi> of the <hi>Vatican Library.</hi>
                  </signed>

               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Let it be Printed, if it ſo pleaſe the Very Reverend Father, Maſter of the Sacred Apoſtolic Palace. </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. de Angelis Archiep. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rb. Viceſger.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <postscript>
                  <p>Let it be Printed,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>F. Raimundus Capiſuccus Ord. Pred. S. P. A. Magiſter.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="approbation">
               <head>The Brief of our Holy Father Pope <hi>Innocent the XI.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VEnerable Brother, Health and Apoſtolical Benediction. Your Book of the <hi>Expoſition of the Catholic Faith,</hi> lately preſented to us, contains ſuch Doctrine, and is compoſed in ſuch a method, and with ſo much prudence, that it is thereby rendred proper to inſtruct the Readers clearly in few words, and to extort, even from the unwilling, a Confeſſion of the Catholic Faith. For which reaſons we do not only think it worthy our commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo to be read and eſteem'd by all. We hope, this Work by the Grace of God will bring forth much Fruit, and will not a little help to propagate the Orthodox Faith, which is our continual care and principal ſollicitude. And in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim, we are more and more confirmed in that good Opinion we have always had of your Vertue and Piety, and we feel an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of thoſe hopes which we had long ſince formed in our ſelves of the Education of the <hi>Dauphin</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and that he who is intruſted to your care, and endowed with inclinations worthy the King his Father, and all his Anceſtors, will receive from you thoſe inſtructions which are proper to the Son of a moſt Chriſtian King, whoſe Birth entitles him both to ſo flouriſhing a Kingdom, and at the ſame time to be a Protector of the Catholic Religion. And this King, who has choſen you amongſt ſo many great men, with which <hi>France</hi> flouriſhes at this time, to ſo great a Province, as is the laying the Foundations of a public happineſs, will no doubt receive an Eternal Glory from the good ſucceſs of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49682:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>your care, according to that Oracle of Scripture, which tells us, <hi>that a Wiſe Son is the Glory of his Father.</hi> Continue then to go forwards chearfully in ſo important a work, eſpecially ſince you have before your Eyes ſuch mighty Fruits of your Induſtry. For we hear, and that from all Parts, and we cannot but feel an exceſs of Joy and Conſolation, amidſt our many Troubles, when we hear, how this young Prince is carried on to vertue with a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fervour, and daily gives new Teſtimonies of Prudence and of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. This we can aſſure you, that nothing is capable of endearing our Paternal affection to you more, than thus to employ your ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Care to inſpire into this young Kings Mind thoſe Maxims, which make a mighty King; that in a riper Age, being hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and victorious, like the King his Father, he may regulate by Holy Laws, and reduce to Chriſtian Manners, Barbarous Nations, and Enemies of the Name of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> as we hope to ſee them ſhortly ſubdu'd to the Empire of this great King, ſince Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſtored to <hi>Europe,</hi> he has ſo fair an opportunity to transfer his victorious Arms into the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> To conclude, Aſſure your ſelf that the Submiſſion and Keſpect which your Letters ſhow you to have towards the Apoſtolic See, and Us, who now poſſeſs it, tho unworthy, for the Government of the Catholic Church, find in Us a mutual affection; the Teſtimonies of which, you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, when any occaſion ſhall preſent it ſelf. With a ſincere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection we give you our Apoſtolic Benediction.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given at <hi>Rome,</hi> at St. <hi>Peters,</hi> under the Fiſhers Ring, <date>the 4th. of <hi>January,</hi> 1679. the third year of our Popedom.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Signed <hi>Marius Spinula;</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>and on the outſide, To our Venerable Brother, <hi>James</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Condom.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49682:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
